<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The gallant ladies, or, The mutual confidence. The first part a novel / translated out of the French.</title>
            <title>Dames galantes. English</title>
            <author>Poisson, Raymond, 1633-1690.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 125 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 71 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55296</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2745</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R40074</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18689913</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18689913</idno>
            <idno type="VID">108168</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55296)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 108168)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1660:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The gallant ladies, or, The mutual confidence. The first part a novel / translated out of the French.</title>
                  <title>Dames galantes. English</title>
                  <author>Poisson, Raymond, 1633-1690.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 123, [5] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of the author's: Les dames galantes, ou, La confidence reciproque.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: [5] p. at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:108168:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:108168:1"/>
            <p>THE GALLANT LADIES, OR, THE Mutual Confidence. A NOVEL. <hi>Tranſlated out of</hi> French.</p>
            <p>THE FIRST PART.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Baldwin</hi> in the <hi>Old Baily.</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:108168:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:108168:2"/>
            <head>To my Worthy Friend, W. Horner ESQUIRE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Generous Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>COntrary to the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of our late Dedicators, who are pleas'd to importune People of Quality with te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Catalogues of thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:108168:3"/>Virtues which neither they, nor their Forefathers ever had the leaſt Title to, and abuſe them with fulſom Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations of their Wit and Judgment, of which they are ſo little guilty, that their Elevated Fortune ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry rarely admits of Common. Senſe: in laying this Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation at your Feet, I ſhall only take the Freedom to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint you, the Subject is ſo adequate to your Capacity, and ſuitable to the Noble Imployment of your Time
<pb facs="tcp:108168:3"/>that I could not without manifeſt wrong to your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Endowments, addreſs it to any body but your ſelf, who are certainly the greateſt Maſter of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigue, that this, or any precedent Age has ever yet produc'd. This Period I confeſs is ſomething long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winded; but, <hi>Sir,</hi> you chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge this, and much more from me; it is due to your incomparable Merit, as all the World will be convinc'd, when it will ſhortly appear,
<pb facs="tcp:108168:4"/>how finiſh'd an Aſs, and elaborate a Coxcomb you are upon Record. When a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Billet doux</hi> of yours to a Perſon that ſhall be nameleſs, which ſome very uncivil Perſons have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to ſome Perſons in Authority, ſhall Publickly inſtruct our Little Smatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers in Love, how to raiſe their Thoughts to a Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phick pitch, and entertain their Female Divinities with ſublimer Nonſenſe This Modern way of Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,
<pb facs="tcp:108168:4"/>as you are modeſtly pleas'd to call it, is a Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent you ought to cheriſh, and which perhaps the neighbring Mineral Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and now and then a Draught of <hi>Banſted</hi> Air, may improve to that degree, as the Whole Nation may be oblig'd to <hi>Surry</hi> for a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, and more refin'd <hi>Longinus. Mac Flec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noe,</hi> who will ever own you to have been his Worthy <hi>Maecenas,</hi> has already aſſur'd us, you were, by his
<pb facs="tcp:108168:5"/>Endeavours, come to be a pretty hopeful, competent Atheiſt: You were then, I ſuppoſe, no further than Speculation; but now are advanc'd to Practice, and ſhew us a new Method of uſing the Scripture, by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troducing it into Love-let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. <hi>Harry Martin</hi> was ſomething too familiar with his <hi>Pigſnye:</hi> But you are as Pathetick as <hi>Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo</hi> himſelf, and as devout in your Expreſſions when you make a Cuckold, as he was
<pb facs="tcp:108168:5"/>when he wrote of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. I ſhould here leave you, but that I think it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to let all Married Women know, how vigorous an Aſſerter you are of their Liberties; I mean not only in your Perſonal Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances, but in the Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter yon beſtow upon the whole Herd of Husbands, whom you ſo generouſly call <hi>Tyrants over their Ladies.</hi> Unhappy Brutes! to fall under your Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. But thrice happy the
<pb facs="tcp:108168:6"/>Fair Sex, in having ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parallell'd an Heroe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver them from the Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and Barbarity of their moſt Tyrannical, Arbitrary Cuckolds. The many real Favours I have formerly received from you, oblig'd me in Gratitude to make you ſome Return; which if I have not done ſo effectually as you deſerve, I muſt needs beg your Pardon. Dear, Dear Mr. <hi>Horner,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt Devoted, Faithful, Humble Servant, &amp;c.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:108168:6"/>
            <head>THE GALLANT LADIES, OR, THE Mutual Confidence.</head>
            <p>NOT long after the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of the <hi>Tuilleries</hi> was finiſh'd, the Counteſs of <hi>Marignan</hi> had a mind to go thither to take the Air. After ſhe had walked ſome turns, ſhe ſat down upon a Bench, where ſhe found a Woman whoſe Face ſhe thought was not unknown to her. Yet, what Idea ſoever ſhe had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd of her, ſhe could not call her perfectly to mind, till after ſome at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive conſideration they at laſt knew one another, and embraced
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:108168:7"/>with all the kindneſs that could be expected between perſons who love tenderly, and have the pleaſure to ſee one another again, after a long ſeparation. Theſe two Ladies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were married, had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted a ſtrict Friendſhip, and for a long time uſed to converſe under the names of <hi>Iris</hi> and <hi>Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mene.</hi> Upon this account the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs breaking the Ice, Ah, my Dear <hi>Iris,</hi> how am I overjoy'd to ſee you? and yet muſt needs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of you at the ſame time, ſince I am obliged to Chance more than your ſelf, for this happy meeting. My Misfortunes are ſuch, <hi>reply'd</hi> I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, that they have left me no Friends Proof againſt Cenſure, and Abſence; ſo that, Madam, I could not flatter my ſelf with the hopes of your Pardon, when all the World did me ſo much wrong.</p>
            <p>I have always believed, <hi>anſwered the Counteſs,</hi> that your Enemies have contributed more than your
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:108168:7"/>ſelf to the Reports that have been ſpread of your Conduct. Madam, <hi>ſaid Iris,</hi> I can aſſure you, I have never really tranſgreſſed the Laws of true Honour; but I muſt conſeſs, I have often hazarded the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances. The ſame Aſcendant that diſpoſed Men to wiſh well to me, made me rejoice to ſee my ſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved. I will yet own further, that I neglected nothing that was capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of pleaſing them, and that the deſire I had to make them in love with me, was the only employment of my Life. I looked upon a croud of Adorers as the chiefeſt good, and thought nothing equal to the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of being incompaſs'd with them. In fine, Madam, I was what they call a perfect Coquette. That is the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, <hi>ſaid the Counteſs of</hi> Marig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nan, of all Women who have but Beauty enough to make themſelves talked of; the handſomeſt, and the youngeſt are often leaſt guilty; their vanity is more general, their
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:108168:8"/>buſineſs is only to acquire Lovers, &amp; their Conqueſts follow one another ſo cloſe, that they have not leiſure to be ſincerely ingaged. Thoſe who are older, and leſs charming, almoſt always imbarque upon the appearances of a feigned Perſon, and ſometimes puſh their adventures ſo home, that they are Criminal. It is ever dangerous, <hi>reply'd Iris,</hi> to follow that ſort of inclination, and it ſeldom happens that the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order of the Heart has not an effect on the Behaviour, and draws after it abundance of Calamities. I wiſh, <hi>ſaid the Counteſs,</hi> then you would let me know what has befallen you, for yet I am but imperfectly infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, as thoſe are, who have not things from the Original. I can ſtay here as long as I pleaſe, no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy will call me from you, I conjure you therefore to tell me your Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures; I would not requeſt this of you, but I promiſe to give you a Relation of mine afterwards. Upon
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:108168:8"/>theſe Conditions <hi>Iris</hi> could not excuſe her ſelf from ſatisfying the Counteſs's curioſity, and began her Relation after this manner.</p>
            <div type="history">
               <head>The Hiſtory of <hi>Iris.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YOU know, Madam, with what conſtraint my Mother brought me up, that ſhe hardly gave me the freedom of improving your Friendſhip. It is true alſo, that ſince you were married, and that your Husband carried you down into the Country, I had no more communication with the World. The weariſom life I led, made me fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy it a great pleaſure to be no longer ſubject to the haſty reproofs of my Mother, and her Commands, ſo op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to my inclinations. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, like a Fool, that when I was married, I ſhould be Miſtreſs of my Actions. This was it that cauſed me to accept the firſt offer my Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:108168:9"/>made me of an Husband, and without examining whether my Heart approved my Friends choice, I married the Vicount of—</p>
               <p>In the mean time, my Mother, who had a mind that I ſhould never be free from her ſeverity, gave my Husband large inſtructions how he ſhould govern me. There are few of them who are not very ready to purſue ſuch Maxims: So that quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after I was married he let me know his intentions, which ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed very different from what I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to my ſelf. He told me, I muſt confine my viſits among my Relations, and ſome Godly Perſons of my Mothers acquaintance; he appointed what time I ſhould ſpend in Devotion, but allowed me none for Pleaſure. Now you will be ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd, Madam, to ſee how things are brought about. My Husband told me one day,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Preſidente</hi> is a Judges Wife.</note> that the <hi>Preſidente</hi> of— had asked him for me
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:108168:9"/>and deſired he would give me leave to viſit her. She paſs'd in the World for a Woman of an uneaſie Vertue, a Character not much for my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; ſo that I was not very earneſt to ſee her: but I was ſo ſtrictly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn'd to do it, that I was forc'd to obey. I had form'd ſo unpleaſant an Idea of her, as would hardly have been removed, but that I found her Houſe full of Company, and the Converſation very free. She re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived me very civilly, commended me extremely, and in the moſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging manner that could be, told me, ſhe deſir'd both my Friendſhip, and my Company as often as I could afford it her. Her Husband look'd upon me very earneſtly; and as I was about to take my leave, the Prince of—and the Duke of— came in. The firſt came to make a Propoſition to the <hi>Preſidente</hi> of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſee a general Muſter of the King's Guards that day at <hi>Vincennes.</hi> She made ſome difficulty at firſt;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:108168:10"/>but on condition I would make one of the Party, ſhe conſented. We went in her Coach, for the Duke had occaſion for his another way. The Preſident had a <hi>Meen</hi> very grave and ſerious, and whatever he did was ſo forc'd, that I did not like him at all; not that he wanted Wit, but his way appeared to me ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Politeneſs of the Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers who were there, that as little experience as I had of the World, I could not but find a great deal of difference between them. I will further own to you, <hi>Madam,</hi> that at this firſt Viſit I thought the Prince very amiable. His Air was free, his Humour chearful, his Thoughts were refin'd, and his Expreſſion juſt. I took notice alſo, that I was not diſpleaſing to him, and that he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſought Opportunities of ſaying obliging things to me. I never ſpent a Day ſo much to my ſatisfaction as this; but my Mind was ſo taken up with the Idea of the Prince,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:108168:10"/>which I could by no means efface, that when I found my ſelf alone with my Husband at Night, I thought his Company more trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſom to me than ever it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
               <p>The Inclination I had for the Prince, carried me a great way in a very little time. It was impoſſible for me to avoid loving him; and I believe the ardour wherewith he ſerved me, contributed not a little to my Flame. One day the <hi>Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dente</hi> ſent to me to come and ſup with her, and not queſtioning but the Prince would be there, I ſpar'd no pains or care in dreſſing. I knew that Patches become young People, but my Husband would not ſuffer me to wear any; therefore I took a Box with me, and put them on by the Torch which lighted the Coach. I found the Prince juſt come to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>la Preſidente</hi>'s as I arrived. <hi>I am glad, Madam,</hi> ſaid he to me, as he help'd me out of the Coach, <hi>that I
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:108168:11"/>am here to render you this ſmall Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and ſhall watch all opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of giving you more evident marks of the Poſſion I have for you.</hi> I do not remember what I anſwer'd him, for I was very young, and unexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienc'd; but I know very well I ſpoke to him with a great deal of ſimplicity, and that this Declaration rais'd a mighty diſturbance in my Heart. He has told me ſince, that this Diſorder, and my innocent Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, pleas'd him better, than if I had ſpoken with more Art. The Preſident obſerv'd the pleaſure the Prince had in ſeeing me, and had a mind to converſe with me in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate; ſo that, <hi>Madam,</hi> in leſs than an hour I was forc'd to hear another Declaration of Love, which I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd no better than the firſt, tho for different Reaſons; for if my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination to the Prince made me ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, you may well judge, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difference I had for the Preſident caus'd me not to anſwer him. After
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:108168:11"/>Supper we had a Conſort of Voices and Inſtruments, which did not laſt long, becauſe ſome of the Ladies had a mind to play. You know, <hi>Madam,</hi> thoſe who are of that hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, are inſenſible to all other Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions. The Preſident ſeeing I did not play, told me he would take care to divert me, on condition I would contribute no leſs to his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction; in order to which, he ſent for the Muſick again, which he knew I liked. This was a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncture pretty nice for a Woman ſo little vers'd in the Affairs of Love as I was: for the Prince and the Preſident beſieg'd me by turns. When the firſt took me out to dance, the other told me, that Courtiers knew not how to love, and that they took more pleaſure in ruining a Womans Reputation. than in the Favours ſhe could be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow upon them. This Truth hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred not my Kindneſs to the Prince; on the contrary, it increas'd my
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:108168:12"/>Averſion for him who told it me. I continued my Viſits to the <hi>Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dente,</hi> which my Husband approved of, telling me, he wiſh'd I would conform my ſelf in all my Actions to that Vertuous Lady. I ſaw the Prince almoſt every day at her Houſe, but not with ſuch freedom as to diſcover our Thoughts to one another; which made him think fit to give me this Billet there.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>SHall I never ſee you,</hi> Madam, <hi>but in a Crowd of People who beſiege you, and will not give me leave to acquaint you with that Paſſion you have inſpir'd? Alas!</hi> Madam, <hi>I fear all, and hope nothing; whilſt you give me not ſo much as one comforting look: and whatſoever mine expreſs, you love me not enough to underſtand what they mean. If you would have this Secret conceal'd, take care to cheriſh it by ſome Mark of Pity; for unleſs you aſſiſt me, it is impoſſible for me not to diſcover it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:108168:12"/>
I read this Note over an hundred times; but I was ſtrangely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex'd how to anſwer it: for my Mother was one of thoſe old-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion'd Ladies who would not have young Folks know how to write to one another, and never let me learn any more than enough to ſign my Marriage-Contract. However, I was reſolved to anſwer him; but I could not do it without truſting a Wench that waited on me, call'd <hi>Limelville,</hi> becauſe ſhe wrote pretty well, and I had a mind to make uſe of her Hand, and her Advice, in this important Diſpatch. After ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Beginnings of my Letter, which did not pleaſe me, at laſt I pitch'd upon this.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>IT was not without ſome difficulty that I reſolv'd to write to you, and I found it no leſs hard how to expreſs my ſelf. But you muſt not ſo much as one minute believe I want
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:108168:13"/>Gratitude, ſince you have diſcover'd what favourable Thoughts you have of me: And I will ſuffer no body to inſtruct me how to love, but your ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having ſpent all the Morning in framing this <hi>Billet doux,</hi> I had juſt done ſealing it, when my Husband came into my Chamber. I held it ſtill in my Hand, and going haſtily to put it in my Pocket, I unhappily let it fall. My Husband ſeeing a Paper fall between me and <hi>Limel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville,</hi> took it up immediately, and being naturally ſuſpicious, went out again preſently to ſee what was in it. I preſently perceiv'd I had loſt it, and look'd about for it to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; you may imagine how I was alarm'd. But there was ſo little time to loſe, that without any more Reflexions we ſoon contriv'd how to bring our ſelves off. The Billet was in <hi>Limelville</hi>'s Hand, and ſhe plaid the Part we had agreed on with as much addreſs and aſſurance,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:108168:13"/>as was requiſite. I was ſtill inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting her, when ſhe perceived my Husband ſtealing ſoſtly towards us, to hear what we ſaid. <hi>Well,</hi> Madam, ſaid ſhe to me, raiſing her Voice, <hi>you ſhall either give me the Note again which you took from me, or let me quit your Service. It is no ſuch Crime ſure to write to a Man I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to marry; let me beg of you, not to leave me in this uneoſie condition.</hi> To keep up the Scene, I ſwore to her I had not ſeen her Billet; but the more I aſſured her, the more ſhe perſiſted that I had it.</p>
               <p>My Husband was mightily pleas'd to hear us talk thus. <hi>Limelville</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought him to uſe his Intereſt with me to reſtore her Note, and that with ſo much concern, and real ſigns of anger, that he was decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by them, and at laſt gave her the Letter, and withal rallied her for having ſuch a tender Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence with a Man. Thus ſhe came off by a pretended Intrigue, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:108168:14"/>the ſame Billet which had been in my Husbands poſſeſſion, I convey'd that very Night into the Prince's Hands, at the Preſident's Houſe. From this time forwards I had no more need either of Secretary or Interpreter: My Paſſion taught me more in eight days, than I ſhould have learnt in half a year, if Love had not been in the caſe. But I was continually plagued with the Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent's Addreſſes, which were the only Subjects of his Diſcourſe, and he would needs perſuade me, I ought to make him ſome return; but find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he gain'd no ground upon me, and believing my Husband ſtood in his way, he waited impatiently for the Spring, which would oblige him to go to his Command in the Army. I viſited his Lady frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and found her not altogether ſo ſevere as the World took her to be. She very patiently ſuffer'd the Duke to praiſe her white Hands and Neck, which ſhe was not very ſcrupulous to ſhew.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:108168:14"/>
The King, who ſtays not for fair weather to extend his Conqueſts, in <hi>February</hi> march'd to invade the County of <hi>Burgundy;</hi> and my Husband having Orders to be with his Regiment, left me alone at <hi>Paris.</hi> All things at this time ſeem'd to contribute to my Happineſs; my Mother went into the Country too, and I forgot, <hi>Madam,</hi> to tell you, that my Husband deſir'd the Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and his Lady to have an eye to my Conduct, and charg'd me to do nothing without their advice. The firſt uſe I made of my Liberty after his departure, was to advertiſe the Prince of it, and to give him an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation in the King's Garden. I was preparing my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> meet him, when the Preſident came to ſee me: He began his Vint with a long Diſcourſe, how reſerv'd I ought to live, whilſt my Husband was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to the Chance of War; that now was my time to eſtabliſh my Reputation in the Eye of the World:
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:108168:15"/>and added, that the Care of it was recommended to him. But when after theſe grave Admonitions, he would have ſpoken to me of his Love, I ſpitefully ask'd him whether that Article was included in his Commiſſion? <hi>No, it is not,</hi> ſaid he <hi>but if you do not uſe me well, I aſſure I will be reveng'd of you for that Coldneſs wherewith you have hitherto treated me.</hi> I was all this while it the worſt Humour that could be for I thought my time very ill ſpent, which I might have paſs'd in Converſation much more accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to me: But there was no reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, I was ſain to be patient two hours, and ſhould hardly have come off ſo, if his Lady had not come in and then he left us together. <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſomething,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>to ſpeak <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> you in private, I deſire we may not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> interrupted.</hi> So I order'd my Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to deny me, and we went pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently into my Cloſet, where ſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoke to me much after this manner.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:108168:15"/>
                  <hi>You are not ignorant,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>Dear Child,</hi> (for ſo ſhe was wont to call me) <hi>that I have a ſincere Kindneſs for you, and am overjoy'd to ſee you happy. For this reaſon, I have a mind to give you ſome Advice, which may not be unneceſſary to you, if you deſire your Quiet. And I aſſure you, it is a great eaſe to a Woman to have the World think her a Perſon of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular and prudent Behaviour. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if we are wiſe, we ought to ſettle an Opinion of our Reputation, before we think of our Pleaſures. To com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs this, we muſt ever ſtudy to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear well outwardly, and deny our ſelves Trifles, ſo we make ſure of what is ſolid. Thoſe who follow this method, have great Privileges above others, and whatſoever they do is ſtill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted to their advantage. By this means I have hitherto ſucceeded well enough, having ſacrific'd the firſt part of my Life to enjoy the remainder with more freedom. To proceed, I ſhould not deſire to be ſo intimate
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:108168:16"/>with you, but that I have obſerv'd you are very diſcreet. I would have you fix your Eyes and your Heart, limit your Deſires, and have a care that your Ambition to pleaſe all men, rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der you not contemptible. It is ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous for a Woman to have ſuch wild Deſigns; ſhe undoes her ſelf, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſucceeds. My Friendſhip will be a conſiderable Protection for you from univerſal Cenſure; and as long as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> live united, you will need to fear no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing on that ſide: However, we will not fail to live pleaſantly. But Child</hi> continued ſhe, <hi>I think you must re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to comply a little with my Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band. I perceive he loves you, and am ſatisfied he ſhould have ſuch a Amuſement, that he may not look to narrowly into my Behaviour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After all this long Preamble, the <hi>Preſidente</hi> confeſs'd ſhe lov'd the Duke, and that he was not ingrate ful. She added, That to avoid truſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her own Women, ſhe would be glad to have a She-friend, whom ſhe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:108168:16"/>might confide in, to make Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to walk with; and that we ſhould admit the Prince into our Society, for ſhe knew well enough we had an Intrigue between us. I approv'd all ſhe ſaid, only I could not agree to fix my Thoughts upon one Object, that Article I excepted out of the Treaty with a mental Reſervation. She told me further, That the <hi>Chevalier du</hi>—and the Count of— whom I had ſeen at her Houſe, were not fit to be truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with our Secrets; and deſir'd me not to entertain them. I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd her every thing, and did ſtand much upon breaking my Word. When this Diſcourſe was over, ſhe invited me home to ſup with her. My Porter told me, as I went out, that the Prince had been to wait on me. I believe his impatience to be alone at the Rendezvous, made him come to know why I fail'd. The Preſident receiv'd me very chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and gave me a thouſand Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:108168:17"/>of his Friendſhip. I daz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his Eyes with a ſuperficial Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance, which he liked the better, becauſe he thought it ſincere. You will wonder, <hi>Madam,</hi> to ſee me ſo inlightned in the Affairs of Gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try in ſo ſmall a ſpace of time: But Love, as ſoon as we are ſenſible of it, takes care to initiate us in his Myſteries; and beſides, I had ſo lately receiv'd Inſtructions, that I could not chuſe but be ſomething improv'd. As ſoon as I came home, I found this Note from the Prince.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>YOu are more knowing than I thought; and I find you are able to inſtruct me However, it is not ſo eaſie for you to abuſe me, as you believe; and I begin now to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what your Proceedings mean. You make an Aſſignation, and fail. When I come to inquire the Reaſon of it, your Servants tell me you are not within, at the ſame time I find the Preſident's Coach at your Door. I
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:108168:17"/>give place to this Happy, Worthy Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val, and thank you heartily for reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring me to my ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I could not endure to leave the Prince in this miſtake; and though it were after midnight, I preſently ſent him this Anſwer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>WIſe men never judge wholly by Appearances; and I am far enough from being guilty, to give you any reaſon to do ſo: but you are very much to blame, for entertaining ſo diſadvantageous an Opinion of me. Take care to find out the Truth your ſelf; for I aſſure you, I am not enough your Friend to night to take any pains to convince you of my Innocence; and I doubt not but you will have a hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Task to repair the Wrong you do me, than I ſhall have to perſuade you that the Preſident is my Averſion, and that I was powerfully diſpos'd to love you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:108168:18"/>
If Lovers eaſily entertain Suſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions, they are are as eaſily rid of them. The Prince came to ſee me next day, we ſoon came to an <hi>éclair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſſement,</hi> and Peace was concluded. Though the Winter was not yet quite over, yet we had now and then ſome fair Weather, which I was ſure not to loſe; and for all <hi>Madam la Preſidente</hi>'s Advice, went to <hi>Vincennes,</hi> where I found all the young People that ſtaid in Town. Here I met the <hi>Chevalier du</hi>— whom I had often ſeen at her Houſe. He came up to my Coach, and I alighted, and walked with him a pretty while. You may well think, <hi>Madam,</hi> that he ſaid ſoft things to me, and that I was not angry to hear them. We began a kind of an Intrigue, but it came to nothing becauſe he went away next day to the Army, and was kill'd in that Campagne. I had abundance of ſuch Adventures, which I paſs over,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:108168:19"/>and ſhall confine my ſelf to thoſe only which have caus'd all the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes of my Life.</p>
               <p>I told the <hi>Preſidente</hi> the little Miſunderſtanding between me and the Prince, and ſhe generouſly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd to be our Mediatrix; but there was no need of it, our Hearts had already prevented that good Office. In return of my Conſidence in her, ſhe let me know, that ſhe never had any difference with her Duke. <hi>I have never the better Opinion,</hi> ſaid I, <hi>of your Kindneſs for one another, for that. A peaceable Love is too like Matrimony; without quarrelling ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, we ſhould loſe the Pleaſure of Reconciliation; and without Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, the Glory of ſurmounting them: there is more in it than People fancy, to have the uncontroll'd Enjoyment of the Delights of an Amorous Intrigue. What would you have me ſay?</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inued I: <hi>I proteſt I ſhould not hate that man whoſe Jealouſie made him a little rough with me. Pardon me
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:108168:20"/>there,</hi> ſaid the <hi>Preſidente; no body ſure can talk as you do, unleſs they have a deprav'd Taſte. We will not diſpute of Taſtes,</hi> anſwer'd I; <hi>for I am ſatisfied, all the Brisk Women in Town are of my Opinion; for Concern is almoſt always a ſign of Love. My Dear,</hi> ſaid the <hi>Preſidente, you are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry knowing for a Woman that was married ſo young; and I fear you do not diſtinguiſh in this Caſe between a Husband and a Lover. Yes, but I do,</hi> replied I; <hi>for that which would appear intolerably whimſical in the firſt, would charm me in the laſt Then you have tried them both,</hi> ſaid ſhe. <hi>No, never,</hi> ſaid I; <hi>all theſe Differences that I ſpeak of, are but Speculative.</hi> It was to no purpoſe for me to maintain my Opinion, for ſhe would never agree to it. We lived thus near two Months pretty quietly, at leaſt among our ſelves for as to my particular Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, I had a mixture of Melancholy and Pleaſure.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:108168:20"/>
You may remember, <hi>Madam,</hi> if you pleaſe, that I told you I ſaw the <hi>Chevalier du</hi>— at <hi>Vincennes,</hi> and that we began an Intrigue, which was to have been carried on at his return from the Army. The poor Youth was kill'd at the Siege of <hi>Dole,</hi> and the firſt News I had of it was from the Count <hi>de</hi>— I wept bitterly when I heard it, which had ſuch effect upon the Count, that he fancied my Heart was ſuſceptible of a true Affection; and therefore endeavour'd to comfort me. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member he talk'd to me above two hours, to no great purpoſe; till at laſt looking ſtedfaſtly upon me, he ſaid it was a great Bleſſing for a man to be belov'd by me; and aſſured me, he would omit nothing that might deſerve that Honour. At thoſe Words I liſten'd to him, I look'd upon him, and did not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid him to hope.</p>
               <p>Some days paſs'd without ſeeing him; but his return from the Army
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:108168:21"/>chear'd up my Spirits. Being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a neceſſity of carrying Matters fairly with the <hi>Preſidente</hi> and her Husband, and the Prince, I told the Count he muſt not come ſo often as he did to my Houſe; but that I would meet him at ſome Ladies Houſes of his Acquaintance and Friends: and I was mightily pleas'd to find him always there before me. He is certainly a man of a penetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Wit, which made him quickly ſee into the bottom of my Behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and ſhew'd him, there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in my Temper to be depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon. He went into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try for ſome time; and when he came back, I had quite forgot him. Sure he had made but little progreſs in my Heart; for I never heard of him there ſince. One day reſlect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon this half Adventure, I ſaid to my ſelf, <hi>See what comes of Love without Oppoſition. If I found more Obſtacles to remove, more Quarrels to make up, and that my Mind and my
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:108168:21"/>Heart were more employ'd, I ſhould not run ſo from one thing to another, and take ſuch pains to intangle my ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All this while my Happineſs ſeem'd to be ſirmly eſtabliſh'd. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Husband nor Mother talk'd of coming to Town, and I manag'd the Preſident with ſuch dexterity, that he imputed my Coldneſs to him, wholly to my rigid Vertue. But at laſt things began to turn, and I ſhould have had Affliction enough, had I been capable of ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king any thing much to heart. The Prince's Friends obliged him to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; and I believ'd, that if this En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement did not quite break off our Commerce, it would at leaſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitate him to ſave the Appearan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. However, things prov'd quite otherwiſe; he married a Woman that had neither Beauty nor Worth, and was only conſiderable for the Money ſhe brought him: So that finding nothing either in her Perſon
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:108168:22"/>or her Mind, that could engage him, he ſoon diſpens'd with thoſe Duties which a Wife to his liking would have oblig'd him to, and I had no reaſon to fear ſhe had robb'd me of his Heart. I reſolved to ſee the Princeſs my ſelf; and I had no reaſon to repent of my Viſit. But, <hi>Madam,</hi> the Pleaſures of Love are built upon ſuch tottering Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that they are liable to ſudden Change. Till now I lay ſecure, if I may ſo expreſs my ſelf, in the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom of Proſperity; but at laſt my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time was come to undergo the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities that Gallantry expoſes Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to.</p>
               <p>The Preſident, who began to be weary of my Reſiſtance, and was not willing to think his want of Merit the Cauſe of it, caſt about to diſcover which way my Heart was inclin'd. To effect this the better he corrupted my Woman, who had help'd me off ſo well with my firſt Letter. Perfidious <hi>Limelville</hi> told
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:108168:22"/>him all I have related to you, not forgetting either the <hi>Chevalier du</hi>— or the Count of— However, the Preſident's Love not going beyond his Prudence, he was willing to be convinc'd by being an Eye wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of my Intrigues. One Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, when the Prince was with me in my Cloſet, <hi>Limelville</hi> ſent the Preſident word of it: This Advice diſturb'd hm; but as all Lovers are apt to flatter themſelves, he fancied at firſt I did not much value the Prince's Company; and to be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied whether I did or no, order'd his Wife to ſend for me to play at <hi>Ombre</hi> with her. I told the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger, I could not poſſibly come, becauſe I was to anſwer a long Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I had receiv'd from my Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band; believing this Excuſe would bring me off: but it provok'd the Preſident more. He perceiv'd I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd to keep cloſe where I was; therefore to expoſe me, he propos'd to his Wife and the Duke to come
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:108168:23"/>to my Houſe. I had taken no mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures to hinder my ſelf from being ſurpris'd, and knew nothing of their coming till they were in my Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber. I went thither as faſt as I could, and would have led them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another Apartment; but the Preſident puſh'd me back, and taking a <hi>Flambeau,</hi> went directly into my Cloſet, where he found the Prince in ſome diſorder. They ſaluted one another in ſuch a manner as you may imagine, and came back toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into the Room where his Wife ſtaid with the Duke; after which, he made me go along with him into that Chamber where I would have carried him at firſt.</p>
               <p>I had not time to conſider much what I ſhould ſay, to excuſe my not coming to his Houſe, and my being found in private ſo cloſe with the Prince. Shall I tell you, <hi>Madam?</hi> his Jealouſie was ſo great, that he gave me a Box on the Ear with all his ſtrength. After this tranſport
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:108168:23"/>of his Rage, he ſaid all that could confound me with ſhame. I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how I did to go through with it. The truth is, I was ſo little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd, that I held it my beſt way to take his Blows in good part: So that in ſtead of anſwering his Fury with the like, I fancied the Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, who was otherwiſe a Man of very good temper, could not have been ſo violent, without an Ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient of Jealouſie, which is never without Love. When he left off ſpeaking to me, I would have juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied my ſelf, by telling him, I could not help entertaining the Prince, for fear he ſhould ſuſpect I had ſome other Amorous Deſign on foot, that hindred me from doing him that Favour. <hi>Hold your tongue, falſe Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> interrupted he; <hi>I know all your Intrigue:</hi> And then told me my Adventures with the Prince, the <hi>Chevalier,</hi> and the Count; of which, he ſaid, <hi>Limelville</hi> had inform'd him. After this, I had no more
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:108168:24"/>to do, but to ſubmit, which was cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly my beſt way.</p>
               <p>While I was thus employ'd with the Preſident, the Prince and the <hi>Preſidente</hi> paſs'd their time but little better: The firſt apprehended I would reconcile my ſelf to the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident by betraying him; the other was ready to die for fear I ſhould diſcover all the Secrets ſhe had tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted me with, to her Husband. But neither of them had any reaſon to trouble themſelves; all that I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd, was to convince him, that he did me wrong to be jealous of me; and the Intereſt I had not to exaſperate him, arm'd me with ſo good Reaſons, and made me ſo elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, that at laſt I brought him to beg my Pardon. So we went back again to the Company pretty well reconcil'd, conſidering how deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately we had fallen out.</p>
               <p>The Prince and Madam <hi>la Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dente</hi> were a little ſurpris'd, that ſuch a terrible Storm was ſo ſoon
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:108168:24"/>over. I endeavoured to find by their Eyes what they thought; but they were ſo taken up with looking upon one another, that they took no notice how narrowly I obſerv'd them. As Play was only the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of this Viſit, which was ſpent quite in another manner, we ſoon broke up: When they were gone, I turn'd away <hi>Limelville;</hi> and the Preſident, to whom ſhe complain'd, reſus'd to intercede for her. I thought now I was pretty well out of this troubleſom Buſineſs, but I was deceiv'd; for afterwards the face of Affairs was extremely al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd. <hi>Limelville</hi> told the <hi>Preſidente</hi> all ſhe knew, and was no leſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municative to the Prince. I was aſtoniſh'd next day to find them both very cold to me, without gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving me any reaſon for it: Indeed I did much trouble my ſelf to find it out. We went to walk at the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenal, where the Duke came to us. He gave his Hand to the <hi>Preſidente,</hi>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:108168:25"/>and the Prince began to converſe with me in ſuch a forc'd manner, that he had much ado to tell me, he was ſorry for my Misfortune the day before. I quickly gueſs'd he was chang'd, by his ſtiff way. Nor was the Duke better ſatisfied with Madam <hi>la Preſidente</hi>'s Proceedings; ſo that I believe all our thoughts at that time were much alike. Upon this occaſion, <hi>Madam,</hi> I remembred what the Preſident had told me of the Prince's Humour, and he began to appear leſs and leſs worthy of my Eſteem. What I once thought an Accompliſhment in him, I now look'd upon to be nothing but Rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: On the contrary, every thing the Preſident did, ſeem'd very graceful to me. Yet I muſt needs confeſs theſe thoughts went out of my Head as faſt as they came in; but at laſt they return'd ſo often, that though my Deſign was not to make him perfectly happy, I was at leaſt deſirous to make an intimate
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:108168:25"/>Friend as long as I lived. To ſpeak truth, I did not yet underſtand my ſelf, and was very incapable of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>having my ſelf as I ought in ſuch Circumſtances.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Preſidente,</hi> for her ſhare, was grown ſo weary of the long Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity ſhe enjoy'd with her Duke, that ſhe had already reliſh'd the Prince's inſinuating Temper; and I doubt not but ſhe met him half way; for I am ſure of himſelf he was not very forward to court a Lady old enough to be his Mother, or his Governeſs. I perceiv'd plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſhe apprehended me no leſs than the Duke; and ſhe had reaſon to fear, that her thwarting me would provoke me to diſabuſe the World in general, and her Husband in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, of the falſe Opinion they had of her Vertue: But ſhe had ſo much wit, and was ſo nearly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd to preſerve her young Lover, that ſhe made it her Buſineſs to abuſe me.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:108168:26"/>
One day, as I was walking with her in the Garden, I had the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to ſee her ſetch three or four Turns at a mighty rate, and to hear her ſigh as if ſhe were deeply afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. I was impatient to know the meaning of theſe Tricks, when ſhe began her ſelf, by telling me, That the Humour and Way of Living in the World was very dangerous for Women; that it was inconſiſtent with their Repoſe; that ſhe had found more Delight in her ſevereſt Retirements, than in all the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſhe had ever allow'd her ſelf. <hi>To conclude, Madam,</hi> ſaid ſhe to me, <hi>I could not poſſibly conceal my Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly and my Sighs from you any longer, which are the Effects of a Conflict in my Breaſt, between a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of Inclination for the World, and a Reſolution to abandon it for ever.</hi> I did not oppoſe her Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, becauſe I was ſure they were affected, and that the World had her faſt enough. I prais'd her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:108168:26"/>for chuſing the ſolid part; and when ſhe told me that her Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience confirm'd her in thoſe pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Intentions, I promis'd her, that when I had as much as ſhe, I would not fail to follow her Example. This entertain'd us five or ſix days, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring which I often met with the Duke, who endeavour'd to make me joyn with him in being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veng'd of her. But I had a mind to have all the Glory of it my ſelf, and ſhould have been ſorry to ſhare it with any body elſe.</p>
               <p>I learnt not long after, that the <hi>Preſidente</hi> ſaw the Prince often by viſiting his Wife, under colour of Friendſhip, to make up Differences between them; to effect which, I was ſacrific'd. I reſolved then in my turn to make her a Victim to my Reſentment; yet would not do it ſo baſe a way, as to betray the Secrets ſhe had truſted me with, but choſe a more refin'd ſort of Revenge. One day that I was at her Houſe,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:108168:27"/>after her Husband had diſcours'd in private to me a pretty while, ſhe ask'd me, as ſhe uſed to do, what he ſaid to me, <hi>He ſpoke to me,</hi> ſaid I, <hi>of the Evening that he found the Prince with me, and repreſented to me the prejudice a Woman does her ſelf, by having to do with a man of his Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter. It is as little for a Womans Reputation to entertain my Husband,</hi> ſaid the <hi>Preſidente, as the Prince. Since things,</hi> replied I, <hi>continue ſtill in the ſame ſtate you firſt ſettled them, I ſee no reaſon you have to find fault now. Yes,</hi> anſwer'd the <hi>Preſidente, I have now ſome Scruples of Conſcience. I'll take them upon me,</hi> ſaid I, <hi>and you ſhall allow me to preſerve a Friend whom I have an infinite value for.</hi> At laſt we were ſo exaſperated againſt one another, that we were utterly irreconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. I was inform'd, that her Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for the Prince tranſported her beyond all bounds; yet I was not jealous, though certainly to a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:108168:27"/>who pretends to any thing of Beauty, nothing can be more inſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable, than to ſee another, who is neither ſo handſom, nor ſo young, deprive her of a Servant. My Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity to know what paſs'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween her and the Prince, made me think of corrupting one of his Footmen, which was no hard mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to do; and by this means I learnt, that the <hi>Preſidente</hi> and her new Lover were to go and ſpend a day at an Houſe of her Husbands in <hi>Brie,</hi> five or ſix Leagues from <hi>Paris,</hi> where he had importun'd me a great while to go along with him, and paſs a few days. Hitherto I had refus'd him; but now I preſs'd him as much, and without telling any Reaſon for it, conjur'd him to keep the Deſign of our Journey private. I made him conſent to let the Princeſs be of the Party, for ſhe began now to disbelieve the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious Stories that were told her of me. I went to her, and propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:108168:28"/>taking the Air at <hi>Ruell,</hi> which I took to be the beſt way to prevail with her; for ſhe is not a Woman to be depended upon in any thing. It was very well I went this way to work; for ſhe preſently told her Husband, we were to go next day to <hi>Ruell:</hi> which was as he could have wiſh'd, becauſe it was the quite contrary Rode to that he was to take.</p>
               <p>The Preſident was no leſs ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, when his Wife told him, ſhe was to go next day to the Abby of St. <hi>Cyr.</hi> to viſit Madam <hi>Arangonois,</hi> who was retir'd thither.</p>
               <p>Being unwilling to neglect any thing that might compleat my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, I writ a Note to the Duke, deſiring him to meet me at the Place where I was going; but I had little hopes of his coming, becauſe they ſaid he was gone to <hi>Verſailles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I was extremely glad to ſee the Day arrive which was to yield me ſo much ſatisfaction, by expoſing
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:108168:28"/>my Rival: And the Preſident was as well pleas'd too; for he fancied this Journey would be much to his Advantage. He commanded his Servants to go before, and prepare an Entertainment for us; but I or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd one of my Laquais to ſtay them by the way, promiſing to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe them to their Maſter; and then I went to call the Princeſs, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling her, we were not now to go to <hi>Ruell,</hi> becauſe the Dutcheſs of <hi>Aiguillon</hi> was there. She never ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amin'd whither ſhe was to go; for ſhe is a Woman eaſie to be manag'd. From thence we went to meet the Preſident, who ſtaid for us at the Gate of St. <hi>Antoine,</hi> with the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot <hi>B</hi>— and we ſet out very chearfully. The Preſident full of vain Hopes, the Princeſs intent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her Diverſion; for my part, I thought of revenging my ſelf upon Madam <hi>la Preſidente</hi> and my trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous Lover; and the Abbot <hi>B</hi>— was not idle; for he read us a new
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:108168:29"/>Play, which he had juſt fitted for the Stage. My Mind all the while was ſo poſſeſs'd with malicious Joy, that I could not help laughing out aloud ſometimes, to the aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Company, who could not tell what to make of it. At laſt we came to the Houſe, and went in, without any bodies ſeeing of us; for it hapned at a time that all the Servants were abroad at work; and Madam <hi>la Preſidente</hi>'s People were buſie, a getting ſomething for them to eat.</p>
               <p>From the fore-Court we went in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the next, where the Preſident had the ſatisfaction to behold his La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies Coach, and the Princeſs her dear Spouſes Footmen. The ſurpriſe they were in, was not enough to content me yet; my Buſineſs was to let them ſee ſomething more convincing: And to prevent any bodies giving our Lovers any no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice what Company was there to wait on them, I ran before, whilſt
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:108168:29"/>the Preſident was pleas'd to ask his Wives Lacquay ſome Queſtions. The Princeſs follow'd me, and we went as faſt as you may imagine, into a low Apartment, which we found open; we croſs'd a large Hall, and ſeveral Rooms, without meeting any body; ſo that I began to be afraid we were miſtaken: but at laſt I open'd the Door of a Cloſet, where the Princeſs, the Preſident, and my ſelf, found the Prince and his Miſtreſs very lovingly together. She was not at all diſturb'd, or ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd; but with wonderful confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence accoſted me in this manner: <hi>You did not think, Madam, to have met ſo good Company here; I could not ſuffer you,</hi> continued ſhe, <hi>to take the pains to come to a Place where I have any thing to do, without being there my ſelf to bid you Welcome.</hi> I proteſt, <hi>Madam,</hi> ſhe ſpoke to me with that aſſurance, that I was like to forget my Buſineſs was onely to ſurpriſe her. She carried on the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:108168:30"/>Adventure with ſo little diſorder, and her behaviour was ſo open and free, as would have confounded In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence it ſelf. She ſaid a thouſand extravagant things afterwards to her Husband, the Princeſs, and me, not forgetting the Abbot himſelf; and when the poor Gentleman ask'd her what hindred her from going to St. <hi>Cyr.</hi> and why ſhe was lock'd up with the Prince? ſhe anſwer'd, She did it to diſcover my Deſigns, and to convince her ſelf that I was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of her Friendſhip. While the Preſident and his Lady were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaining one another with all that Impudence and Jealouſie could ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt, the Princeſs and her Lord were reaſoning the Caſe much after the ſame manner; and without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the Title he had qualified her with, ſhe ſaid abundance of things to him that exceedingly dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd the Splendour of it. But nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the opening of the Plot would have been according to form, nor
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:108168:30"/>my Revenge compleat, if the Duke had not been there too. He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived my Note, it ſeems, when he came back from <hi>Verſailles,</hi> and did not doubt but I writ it on purpoſe to let him underſtand ſome way or other Madam <hi>la Preſidente</hi>'s Infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, who of late made him believe ſhe was forc'd to break off Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce with himout of true remorſe of Conſcience, and Religious Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations. Deſirous therefore to find out her Hypocriſie, he ſtaid no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than juſt to ſhift his Clothes, and with one Page onely came away full ſpeed to the Place where I dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted him. Nor could he come at a more ſeaſonable time for his Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; for he had but to liſten a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, to be inform'd of all that he was ignorant of; and the Princeſs took care to open his Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. The Duke is not a man who eaſily pardons Faults of this nature; and if he be ſevere ſometimes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe, you may judge how he
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:108168:31"/>treats the Guilty. He thought now he might without any ſcruple take his full ſwing of Revenge; and without conſidering that Husband &amp; Lover were by, ſet himſelf to ral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly her in that manner as is natural to him, and indeed to all the <hi>Gaſcons. Madam,</hi> ſaid he, addreſſing himſelf to the Preſident's Lady, <hi>I came on purpoſe really to have my ſhare of your ſweet Meditations, to ask you how far you are improv'd by them, and if they are yet prevalent enough to efface the Love you have ſo often ſworn to me: But I ſee plainly,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued he, <hi>the New Guide of your Conſcience has a greater Influence in the change of your Behaviour, than the holy Reſolutions you were pleas'd to make againſt me; and that he had quite extinguiſh'd thoſe Flames, which I had reaſon to believe I had pretty well fomented for a year together. Beſides, give me leave to tell you, that it was a great ſatisfaction to me to behold you return into a Courſe from
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:108168:31"/>which I imagin'd I had diverted you: But I ſhould be juſtly guilty of all the Crimes of your New Intrigue, if I ſhould not now take my turn to exhort you to be more faithful to</hi> Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur le Preſident, <hi>than you have been hitherto; and if I did not caution him not to be any longer cheated with the falſe glittering Tinſel of your imaginary Vertue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whilſt the Duke ſpake thus, the miſerable Husband, his Wife, and the Prince were ſo confounded, that they could not open their Mouths; not but that they had enough to ſay, but the truth is, People in their condition are a little indiſpos'd to Eloquence. The Princeſs, who heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the Duke all this while with inexpreſſible pleaſure, could not help crying out when he had done, <hi>Bleſs me! what prodigious Wit he has!</hi> There was no occaſion of this, to make him begin again upon ſo copious a Subject. <hi>What,</hi> Monſieur le Preſident, ſaid he, <hi>are you ſtill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:108168:32"/>of your Ladies Conduct? Will you never open your Eyes, to ſee the Injury ſhe does you? Don't you know, that when you ſued one of your own Robe, and would come to no Terms of Agreement with him, ſhe, good Lady, was at no diſtance in the World with him, and ſacrific'd yours, and her Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour too, to her immoderate Paſſion? Where have you lived, Man, that you know not the Marquis</hi> de St—<hi>was her particular Friend, and that I my ſelf, without vanity be it ſpoken, have not received the leaſt of her Favours?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You may gueſs, <hi>Madam,</hi> what the Duke ſaid was ſufficient to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe <hi>Madam la Preſidente</hi>'s affected Wiſdom and Gravity to her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band; but for fear he ſhould go on, ſhe interrupted him to anſwer his Impoſtures, as ſhe was pleas'd to call his raillying her Intrigues. As for the Prince, he was ſo exaſperated that fearing he would quarrel with the Duke, which might have been laid upon me as the Cauſe, I took
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:108168:32"/>the laſt aſide, and deſir'd him to go out of the Room, and leave the happy Couples to compoſe their Differences without our aſſiſtance. With much ado I perſuaded him to go, and we walk'd into a very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Garden, while the Abbot <hi>B</hi>—took upon him to be the Pleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potentiary to make Peace between the Husbands and Wives. Though the Duke ſaw clearly what I did was much out of Jealouſie, and made no queſtion, but that I had really loved the Prince; yet thoſe Reflections now were food out of his Head. He told me, nothing could be ſo welcome to him as <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam la Preſidente</hi>'s Inſidelity; that ſhe had but got the ſtart of him a few days; that he had already re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to leave her, and apply him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf wholly to me; that what he ſaid was no Eſſect of Melancholy for her Change, but of a ſecret Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance he had for all my Thoughts and Inclinations.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:108168:33"/>
The Duke was Handſom, Libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and Magnificent; and I foreſaw after this bout I ſhould loſe Prince, and Preſident, Wife and all: So that, <hi>Madam,</hi> I muſt confeſs, being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded that the Merit of a young Woman is beſt diſtinguiſh'd by the Multitude of her Adorers; and that to live with any ſatisfaction, it is neceſſary to have one at leaſt; I did liſten to what the Duke ſaid, but did not give my ſelf over to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve all his Vows of loving me eternally; nor did I repulſe him ſo, as to let him fear he was indifferent to me. I had a great Ambition to ſee the Court, where he was in a Station adorn'd with all the Charms that accompany high Birth, great Riches, and conſiderable Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. As he was very diſcerning, and found how fond I was of ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my ſelf in the beſt Company, he flatter'd me ſo far, as to tell me, I could ſee nothing in the Circle it ſelf ſo Beautiful as my ſelf. While
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:108168:33"/>I was hearing what he ſaid to me on this Subject, the Abbot of <hi>B</hi>—came and told me the Preſident en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd to juſtifie his Wife, that they laid all the Miſchief of that days Work at my door, and that both of them would make it their Buſineſs to ruine me when my Husband came home. The Duke, who now began to embrace my Intereſts, was ſo concerned at this Menace, that he deſir'd the Abbot to tell <hi>Madam la Preſidente,</hi> that if ſhe did what ſhe threatned, ſhe ſhould ſeverely pay for it, and that he would make no difficulty to tell all the World what he knew of her Life and Converſation. The Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot diſcharg'd his Commiſſion with a great deal of Addreſs, and in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance things ſeem'd to be made up; but in reality the Preſident could never heartily forgive me.</p>
               <p>Though all I have related to you, <hi>Madam,</hi> looks very Romantick, and that thoſe feign'd <hi>Heroes</hi> never had
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:108168:34"/>any occaſion to eat, I'll aſſure you this is a true Story, and thoſe who were concern'd in it were very hungry; for my part, I found my ſelf ſo, and deſir'd the Abbot to put the Preſident in mind of our Condition, which he did effectually; for his Servants came time enough to get a good handſom Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ready for us. While we were at Table, the Abbot diſcours'd of the Rules of Tragedy, and of the Abbot of <hi>Aubignac</hi>'s Cenſure of Dramatique Poetry. Perhaps he choſe this Subject to ſhew his Parts, becauſe he made Plays himſelf; or rather to divert the Company from talking of what hapned juſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
               <p>From this day forward I ſaw none of them any more, applying my ſelf to appear at Court, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I went with one of the Dukes Siſters. My Face and Shape were more taken notice of there, than either of them deſerv'd; but you
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:108168:34"/>know, Madam, what a Value the World ſets upon Novelty, and there are few who are not impos'd upon by it. To that therefore I muſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute all the fine things the Count <hi>de Saue</hi> and the Marquis <hi>de Villerey</hi> ſaid to me. I diſcover'd ſo much Vanity, that the Duke ſoon repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed he had brought me into ſuch a dangerous Air: And that which ſpoil'd me quite, was, that being one day at <hi>Verſailles,</hi> I perceiv'd the King ask who I was, and look'd upon me in ſuch a manner as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded me that he liked me; and the Duke told me afterwards, that I was not miſtaken. Certainly, <hi>Madam,</hi> when a Woman is once poſſeſs'd with Pride, and the Spirit of Coquetry, ſhe is liable to a World of Extravagances. The Duke having aſſur'd me that the King liked me, I preſently entertain'd ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous Notions of imaginary Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, and believ'd I might come to ſtrike that Great Monarch's Heart.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:108168:35"/>I never went out, but I was as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly dreſs'd, as if I was to appear in the Drawing-room; and I gave my ſelf a looſe in my Behaviour too, that it might be no Impediment to my vain Hopes: Vain I may call them; for they had no Foundation but in my Fancy. As ſoon as theſe Illuſions vaniſh'd, I reconcil'd my ſelf to the reſt of the World, which I overlook'd before, and the Duke took Care to give me all the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions he could invent, to kill, as he ſaid, the Chimera which haunted me ſo. He loved Pomp, and there was hardly a Day paſs'd that he did not give me a ſplendid Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; to which I invited a hundred Ladies, more to gratifie my Vanity, than out of any kindneſs: for it is a Maxim, <hi>That Coquettes love no body but themſelves;</hi> but I did not foreſee, that this Splendour which I took ſuch a pride in, haſtned my Ruine, and plung'd me into great Misfortunes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:108168:35"/>
My Husband received Orders from the King to meet the Count <hi>de Vignory,</hi> who was then Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Binch,</hi> to concert ſome ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Expedition. There hapned ſome Difficulties which retarded their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, and oblig'd my Husband to ſtay longer at <hi>Binch</hi> than he intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>Vignory,</hi> in order to divert him, and perhaps to ſhew him how hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py a man he was, carried him to a Lady of the Neighbourhood in his Government, with whom he ſeem'd to have an habitude; and to let him ſee what Credit he had with her, told him he had recommended a Woman to ſerve her who had lived with me at <hi>Paris.</hi> My Husband's chief Reaſon to conſent to this Viſit, was the deſire he had to learn how I behav'd my ſelf in his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. The Woman that <hi>Vignory</hi> told him of was the treacherous <hi>Limelville,</hi> who no ſooner ſaw my Husband, but to be reveng'd of me for turning her away, you may be
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:108168:36"/>ſure told him all that could make him jealous. She was good at im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving of things, and heightning that to a Crime which was but a Trifle; informing him how I was fallen out with the Preſident, and his Lady, and the Prince, and all that ſhe knew of my Intrigues. He conjur'd her not to diſcover ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant a Secret to any body elſe, and promis'd her, that when he had puniſh'd me, he would ſend for her again to govern his Houſe.</p>
               <p>After <hi>Limelville</hi> had ſo fully in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed him, he made all the haſte he could to execute the Orders he had receiv'd, that he might the ſooner have an occaſion to give the King an Account. <hi>Vignory</hi> and he ſucceeded in their Enterpriſe, which was to ſurpriſe a conſiderable Party of the Enemy, and then my Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band came back to <hi>Paris;</hi> for the News he brought was ſo good, that he did not queſtion being well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, though he came without
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:108168:36"/>particular Order from his Majeſty.</p>
               <p>All this while I was not without Employment; for the Duke is a man pretty hard to be dealt with; he was jealous of every thing, the moſt innocent Actions ſeem'd cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal to hm, and I lived in ſuch conſtraint as began to be intolerable to me. One Evening (the moſt dreadful one of all my Life) it came into my Head to go take the Air at the Point of the Iſland, which was the Quarter of the Town where I lived. You may remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, <hi>Madam,</hi> how the Duke re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach'd <hi>Madam la Preſidente</hi> with an Intrigue ſhe had with the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis <hi>de</hi>— That very man I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunately met, and could not help letting him take me by the Hand to lead me. He had ſeen me lately at <hi>Verſailles,</hi> and ſeveral other Places, and my ingaging way of Behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our had begot a ſtrong Inclination in him for me. I was delighted to converſe with a man who did not
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:108168:37"/>teaze me; for the Duke was now grown as troubleſom to me as the worſt Husband in the World. I let him talk to me therefore a pretty while; and when he had ſaid what he had a mind to, I told him how much I was diſtaſted at all men in general, and then gave him a Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of ſuch a Lover as I could like. After that, I deſcrib'd what an inſufferable Plague it is to bear with Jealous People, or to be ſo ones ſelf; under borrow'd Names I told him all my Husband's and the Duke's Whimſeys, and what juſt Reaſons I had to complain of all who had ever lov'd me; at laſt I open'd my Heart freely to him, without any apprehenſion that any body overheard me. The Night indeed was ſo dark, that I could not perceive the Duke, who fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd us cloſe, wrapp'd up in a great Cloke. I walk'd on ſtill ſeveral Turns, and then took leave of the Marquis, not ſuffering him to lead
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:108168:37"/>me home; where, as ſoon as I came in, I learn'd that the Duke waited for me, and fancied he would wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come me but coldly: and I was in the right; for after he had repeated all that paſs'd between the Marquis <hi>de St.</hi>—and me. from Words he came to Blows; and though too much Indiſcretion was my greateſt Fault, he puniſh'd me as ſeverely as if I had been really guilty. Now as Complaints are very natural on ſuch Occaſions, I was wery elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent upon this Subject, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach'd him bitterly for his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Uſage of me; when of a ſudden I heard a mighty Noiſe in the Street. I was too much afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with my own Concerns, to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble my ſelf with other Peoples; but the Duke put his Head out of the Window, to ſee if the Diſorder which made ſo much noiſe was not caus'd by his own Footmen. It ſeems they did not begin it; but hearing a pretty way off what a
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:108168:38"/>Buſtle there was at my Gate, they ran thither, and without diſcerning Friend from Foe, ſtruck every bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy at random that was in their way. In the heat of the Tumult I diſtinguiſh'd a Man's Voice that was not unknown to me, who call'd all the Servants by their Names whom my Husband left with me when he went away; but they were not there to anſwer, for I had turn'd them all going. You may gueſs how ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pris'd I was to hear them ſo called upon, and could not apprehend who it ſhould be; but that Night, to my ſorrow, produc'd nothing but aſtoniſhing, miſchievous Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents.</p>
               <p>While I was attentive to this Voice, I ſaw my Husband come in like a Man whoſe Fury had over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come his Reaſon; he fell upon all that ſtood in his way, and without any reſpect for the Duke, was run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning full tilt at him, if his loſs of Blood had not weakned him ſo, as
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:108168:38"/>to make him fall down. When he came out of his Swoon, his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants carried him into his Chamber, and put him to Bed; and then his <hi>Valet de Chambre</hi> told me he had been two days in Town, and had a mind to come home alone to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe me. This was all the Fellow could tell me, for he knew no more; but this was enough to make me think I ſhould ſtand in need of the Duke's Protection, which he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd me; and I ſent for a Relation of my Husband's, to deſire him to endeavour to get out of him what Reaſon he had to be ſo tranſported againſt me. This Man, who was always kind enough to me, hapned to come to him juſt as the Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons had done dreſſing him the firſt time. How dangerous ſoever it was for him to ſpeak much, he would needs tell his Kinſman all he knew, and deſir'd him to get me ſecur'd in a Convent, till he had conſulted with my Relations what
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:108168:39"/>to do with me. But now, <hi>Madam,</hi> I muſt tell you what moſt of all inrag'd him againſt me. You have already heard, that he gave the King an Account of his Expedition, who receiv'd him graciouſly, and gave him leave to ſtay a Week at <hi>Paris,</hi> The two firſt Days he was at the Preſident's, who forgot nothing that could load me; and to make me appear more criminal to the World, they contriv'd my Husband ſhould ſuffer himſelf to be ſet upon by Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows hir'd for that purpoſe, that they might have colour to give out I would have had him murder'd. It fell out ſo, that the Duke's Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men wounded him, while their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter was with me; however, he would make no uſe of this Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture againſt any body but me, and when he complain'd moſt of ſo hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid a Deſign, ſtill he juſtified the Duke, becauſe if he ſhould accuſe him, he knew it would be difficult to make People believe it. My
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:108168:39"/>Husband's Kinſman advis'd me pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently to retire, before he had freſh Orders to ſecure me. I took his Counſel, and putting up my Jewels, and ſome Money, I went to the Counteſs of— who receiv'd me with a great deal of Generoſity. Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhe had ſaid all that could com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe my Mind, ſhe dexterouſly took an opportunity to reprove me for having ſo little care of my Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but it was in ſo noble a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and ſo gently, that ſhe made me repent my Folly, without put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting me out of countenance.</p>
               <p>My Husband's Wound did not prove ſo dangerous as was believ'd at firſt; but as faſt as that mended, his Anger increaſed: ſo that I found my ſelf neceſſitated not only to quit <hi>Paris,</hi> but the Kingdom like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. I reſolv'd therefore to put my ſelf into the Protection of the Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs of <hi>Savoye.</hi> The Duke approv'd my Deſign, and the charitable Counteſs gave me Letters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendation
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:108168:40"/>to the moſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Perſons in that Court, where ſhe was well acquainted.</p>
               <p>I went by the Name of <hi>Madam de Courcilly,</hi> and took three Places in the Flying-Coach for <hi>Lyons,</hi> for my ſelf, and a Maid that was newly come to me, and a Man call'd <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> of whoſe Fidelity and Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I had ſome experience: The reſt of the Coach was hir'd by the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beſs of <hi>Bly,</hi> two Nuns, and a rich Banquier of <hi>Genoa</hi> nam'd <hi>Hierony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo Spichetti.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By what I have related to you, <hi>Madam,</hi> you may imagine my Thoughts could not chuſe but dwell upon the troubleſom Accidents of my paſt Life, and thoſe I was then further expoſing my ſelf to; and yet that which made me moſt me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy, was the remembrance of the little Concern the Duke ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd to part with me, which was more grievous to me than all my Husband's ill Uſage; to ſee my ſelf
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:108168:40"/>without Lovers, rendred me the moſt forlorn wretched Creature in the World; and by the coldneſs of his Adieu, I found his Heart was no longer mine. While theſe idle things ran in my Head, the Abbeſs of <hi>Bly</hi> bethought her ſelf of enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the Company with my Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which I had the pleaſure to hear her tell at length, with ſuch falſe ridiculous Circumſtances, that I was twenty times about about to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt he, and tell her ſhe was miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. Judge what a perplexity I was in, when addreſſing her ſelf to me, ſhe would needs have me agree with her, that I was the moſt faulty Woman upon Earth. This made me ſo uneaſie, that at laſt I was fore'd to tell them a Story of a Cock and a Bull, to turn the Diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>Now, <hi>Madam,</hi> pray obſerve the wonderful Events of my Deſtiny: At the very firſt place we baited at, who ſhould I ſee come into the Inn, but the Marquis of <hi>St.</hi>—?
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:108168:41"/>You may think, perhaps, he came by my appointment: No, upon my word, it was perfect Accident brought him thither; for he was going to <hi>Turin,</hi> to Complement their Royal Highneſſes from the King, upon the Recovery of the Dutcheſs of <hi>Savoy.</hi> The truth is, finding a Place empty in the Coach, he diſcharg'd his Poſt-horſes, and took it, without ever dreaming to meet with me. As ſoon as I knew it, I reaſon'd the Caſe with <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> whether I ſhould diſcover my ſelf or no: and we concluded it impoſſible I ſhould be long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd, though I took never ſo much care. Well, I got up into the Coach without diſcovering my ſelf, and did not ſpeak one Word for fear he ſhould know my Voice: But the Abbeſs of <hi>Bly</hi> was not ſo ſilent; for we had hardly gone a Mile, but ſhe ask'd the Marquis whether he knew the Story of the Lady who would have murder'd her Husband? He
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:108168:41"/>anſwer'd, He had not heard of it yet: Upon which, ſhe, who knew it ſo well by heart, began it over again in the ſame Terms, without omitting one Syllable: But when ſhe came to name me, he bid her hold her tongue; or if ſhe muſt tell Tales, ſhe might find enough in her own Convent, without going any further for them. This work'd as I would have it; for the Abbeſs then gave over, and we had ſcarce a Word ſpoken among us all the reſt of that day: And I will own, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> I was ſenſibly oblig'd to the Marquis for reſcuing me ſo nobly from the Abbeſſes ill Language. It hapned, before we came to the Place where we were to lodge that Night, there was a neceſſity of alighting to walk over a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous part of the Way, becauſe it was dark. I ſtaid in the Coach, and the Men went out. The Marquis then perceiving <hi>Bernard</hi> belong'd to me, ask'd him who I was; and was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:108168:42"/>to learn I was the Perſon he lov'd and valu'd ſo much, and whom he had defended againſt the Abbeſs; but he was too diſcrect to ſpeak to me, till he ſaw his time. When we came to the Inn, he gave me his Hand to help me out of the Coach as a Stranger; and as he had me to the Chamber where the Nuns and I were to lie, told me ſoftly how glad he was to meet with me, and how happy he ſhould be to ſerve me. <hi>Spichetti</hi> was as zealous to wait upon me as the Marquis; but I did not give him the ſame Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement. Leſs than this was ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to ſet the Abbeſſes and her Nuns Tongues upon Wheels, who were vex'd to ſee they had more time allow'd them to ſay their Prayers than they cared for. At laſt we came to <hi>Lyons,</hi> where ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no Acquaintance, the Marquis and I took Lodgings in a very good part of the Town, which the <hi>Itali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> directed us to; who, not to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:108168:42"/>his Country, watch'd us very narrowly; and gueſſing by the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſſes Deportment, and my Beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour to him, that we knew one another before, he no longer doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but we had agreed upon this Meeting. But he cunningly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled both this, and whatever other Reaſons he had to be ſo inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive after me; and he and the Marquis contracted a Friendſhip, at leaſt outwardly.</p>
               <p>It being very indecent for me to go along with the Marquis to <hi>Turin, Spicketti</hi> told him he would take care of my Journey, and ſave me the trouble of paſſing the <hi>Alps,</hi> which on the <hi>French</hi> ſide eſpecially are very troubleſom, by reaſon both of their Heighth, and the exceſſive Cold. Though he was not yet perfectly inform'd of my Affairs, he knew I avoided the Perſecution of my Husband: So that joyning his Conjectures to my Silence, which he obſerv'd when the Abbeſs
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:108168:43"/>related my Story, he no longer doubted who I was; but took no notice of what he thought, either to me or the Marquis. All he ſaid to him, was, That he would ſhew me <hi>Provence,</hi> and bring me into <hi>Savoy</hi> by the way of <hi>Italy;</hi> that leaving <hi>Lyons</hi> when he did, and going down the <hi>Rhoſne,</hi> we ſhould be at <hi>Turin</hi> a Fortnight after him. I was well enough pleas'd to ſee <hi>Provence,</hi> and therefore embrac'd his Propoſition, ſo much the rather too, becauſe he ſaid his own Buſineſs requir'd him to be at <hi>Turin</hi> by that time: So we went by Water from <hi>Lyons</hi> to <hi>Avig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non.</hi> But I muſt not forget to tell you, <hi>Madam,</hi> that my Man <hi>Bernard</hi> was much troubled to ſee me truſt my ſelf ſo eaſily in <hi>Spichetti</hi>'s hands. His Kindneſs and Care had ſo far opened his Eyes, as to make him often repine at my Indiſcretion; but there was no avoiding what was deſtin'd for me.</p>
               <p>When we came to <hi>Avignon, Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chetti</hi>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:108168:43"/>lodg'd me at a very fine Caſtle which belong'd to a Friend of his; it ſtood in the Popes Territories, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout two Miles out of Town, where he ſhew'd me all that was worth ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there. After I had been there three Days, I told him it was time to be gone; <hi>I do not intend, Madam,</hi> ſaid he to me, <hi>to take the pains to put you into my Rivals power.</hi> Theſe words ſtruck me like a Thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolt, and made me perceive into what ill circumſtances I had brought my ſelf. They were follow'd by a bundance more which ſerv'd to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his love; that nothing was ſo difficult but he would attempt it to gain my favour, or ſo violent but he would do, if I repuls'd him. I would not own that I believ'd him in earneſt, and turn'd all he ſaid to Gallantry, and Flattery; but that would not ſerve my turn, for he perſecuted me without intermiſſion, at that rate that I was ſeveral times reduc'd to the utmoſt extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:108168:44"/>to eſcape the effects of his bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Paſſion. Till now, <hi>Madam,</hi> I had taſted too much of the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of loving, and being belov'd: Here it was my Fortune to be pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued by a Man who was my aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; for I hated <hi>Spichetti</hi> mortally. If I ſhew'd him the leaſt kindneſs imaginable, that fed his hopes; if I treated him ill, that provok'd him; ſo that nothing but a perfect Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, or Death could put an end to my misfortunes. <hi>Bernard,</hi> who took upon him to be my Privy Counſellor, reproach'd me for not followinig his advice, that I proteſt I was never in ſo perplex'd a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in my life. At laſt, <hi>Hieronimo</hi> calling me one day by my right name, told me, he knew all my Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures, and if I did not reſolve to comply with his deſires in a week, he would ſend my Husband word where I was, and look ſo narrowly to me in the mean time, that I ſhould find it impoſſible to eſcape
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:108168:44"/>out of his Hands. I did all I could to perſwade him I was not the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon he took me for; but it would not do, he knew all my concerns, though I could never learn how he came to be ſo perfectly inform'd. The miſerable condition I was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd to, made me think of nothing now but dying, which I reſolv'd to do rather than ſatisfy the beaſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of this filthy <hi>Italian.</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, I thought I was bound to try all means of delivering my ſelf, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I gave my ſelf quite over to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair, and ſo ſet my ſelf to conſider what was poſſibly to be done to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain my liberty.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> then I took my Jewels, and Bill of Exchange for a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Sum, and ſome ready Money I had left, with the Letters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendation to the Dutcheſs of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and gave them all to <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> when <hi>Spichetti</hi> was out of the way; then telling him, he ſhould be my Governour for the future, I
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:108168:45"/>begg'd him to invent ſome means to free me from the violence which my Tyrant threatned me with. To effect which the better, we agreed he ſhould pretend to leave me, which he preſently put in executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and corrupted the Gardner of the Caſtle where I was, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled him to give me notice how his indeavours ſucceeded.</p>
               <p>The Day which <hi>Spichetti</hi> ſet me, now drawing near, without any hopes of eſcaping, it came into my Head to deſire a little longer time, which he was eaſily perſwaded to grant, becauſe I made him believe his perſeverance had made ſome progreſs in my Heart. He took this opportunity to try if he could dazle me with his Wealth, which he ſet forth with ſuch advantage as would have gone a great way with any Woman but my ſelf, but his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers were thrown away upon me. I had but one Day left now, which <hi>Spichetti</hi> impatiently waited for,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:108168:45"/>when I had notice every thing was ready for my deliverence; which was thus: I was to get out of my Window into the Garden by a Cord Ladder; in the Gardners Houſe there were two Suits of Mens Clothes for me and my Maid, and <hi>Bernard</hi> was to wait for me with Horſes an hundred paces from thence. Though this deſign was well enough contriv'd, yet he might have juſtly queſtioned the ſucceſs of it, if he had conſider'd <hi>Hieronimo</hi> was an <hi>Italian,</hi> in Love, jealous, and ſuſpicious; and ſuch Monſters are hard to be impos'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in things of this importance; but great dangers require ſtrong re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions. One thing happen'd to my advantage; <hi>Spichetti</hi> was taken with a violent Fever, and grew light-headed, but not ſo bad as to hinder him from ordering me to be lock'd up in my Chamber. This caution was to no purpoſe, for I got away as we had contriv'd, and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel'd
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:108168:46"/>all Night without knowing what Road we were in. At laſt, when day broke we found our ſelves on the top of a Mountain from whence we diſcover'd a great many more, which compos'd an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary pleaſant ſolitude. We kept on till Sun-riſe, through untrodden Paths which brought us to an Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitage that ſtood in a very melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly place.</p>
               <p>The charitable Hermits whom I found there, made me as welcome as they could; I had never been on Horſeback before; was very weary, and wanted reſt. The eldeſt of the Hermits led me into a little neat Cell, where I ſlept for ſome time; for my Mind was ſo diſturb'd, that I ſoon wak'd, and found out my good Hoſt, who had got ſome Herbs, and Fruit for me to eat, whoſe cleanly dreſſing made up what they wanted in abundance. Summer was juſt now coming on, and if I had had but the leaſt inclination to
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:108168:46"/>ſpend my life in a Deſart, far from the noiſe, and communication of the World, I ſhould have been much more delighted with this ſolitude; but alas! I was in no condition to hearken to the Muſick of the Birds, to try the neighbouring Eccho's, or to conſider the Beauty of the Rocks; my Head was taken up with other cares. The Hermit, who applied himſelf to entertain me, ſoon per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd I was melancholy, and took occaſion to ſay whatever he thought might comfort me. I obſerv'd more Underſtanding and Politeneſs in his Diſcourſe than uſally Hermits are Maſters of, but what moſt ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd me, was, that after he had looked ſtedfaſtly upon me, he told me, the Clothes I wore did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to my Sex. I ſhould have thought he had diſcover'd it by my Complexion, or my Shape, but that continuing to look upon me, he added, that Love had cauſed all the miſeries of my Life. He ask'd
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:108168:47"/>me the Minute of my Nativity, which I told him as near as I could, and then he ſpoke of ſeveral things in general to me, which gave me warning to take heed of.</p>
               <p>Though what he ſaid was very ſerious, yet I could not forbear laughing, for I could not fancy I ſhould be the happier, or unhappier for being born a Minute ſooner, or later. For all that he inlarg'd his Diſcourſe upon the future, and his Predictions have prov'd very true. I thought it now time to take leave of the Hermit, and was inquiring of him what place I might ſafely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire to, where I might hear how my Affairs went in the World, when my Woman who lay aſleep upon the ground, was bitten by a Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion: This accident forc'd me to ſtay two days longer in the Deſart, during which time the Hermit was ſo civil as to relate his Life to me, which diſcover'd him to be a Man of Quality. His Story had a great
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:108168:47"/>many extraordinary events in it; but I have ſo many to tell you that relate to my ſelf, that I ſhall take notice of the Hermit's no otherwiſe than as they fall into my own Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. At laſt, <hi>My dear Child,</hi> ſaid he to me, <hi>you ſee an unhappy Man, who once gave himſelf wholly over to the World, the remembrance of which ſerves only to renew my repentance of thoſe extravagances, and errours, which her dangerous maxims ingag'd me in. The Knowledge I have of the diſgraces which attend thoſe who are not yet wean'd from her, makes me pity your misfortunes, and prompts me to ſerve you. I have a Friend about two Leagues off, with whom you may ſtay with more convenience, and decency, than in our retirement. There you may ſafely learn what you would be inform'd of, for I will go to</hi> Avignon, <hi>and enquire what is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of</hi> Spichetti, <hi>and ſettle a Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence with a Friend of his, and mine, that I may know what his
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:108168:48"/>Deſigns are. Beſides I muſt tell you, the place where I would have you take refuge, is as pleaſant as this, and ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated upon many accounts. You cannot but have heard of</hi> Vaucluſe, <hi>which was heretofore the dwelling of the famous</hi> Petrarch, <hi>and his charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> Laura. <hi>There you will ſee that wonderful Spring near which ſo many excellent Verſes have been made; but if thoſe objects have ſo much effect upon you, as to make you remember the Loves of that Poet, and his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, they ought alſo at the ſame time to put you in mind, that all things in this World periſh and fade, ſince there remains nothing more of them than ſuch wretched imperfect Footſteps.</hi> I beſought the Hermit to relate the Loves of <hi>Petrarch,</hi> and when I had heard them, was more impatient than before of ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Habitation.</p>
               <p>Before I took my leave of him, he gave me a Letter to his Friend, and a Book of <hi>Petrach</hi>'s Poems in <hi>Italian,</hi>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:108168:48"/>for which, and the reſt of his favors I thank'd him with all the marks of gratitude I could expreſs. He gave <hi>Bernard</hi> a ſtrict charge not to forſake me, and then ſhew'd us the Way that would bring us to <hi>Vau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſe.</hi> At Night we came to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>de Mezelon</hi>'s (ſo was the Lady call'd to whom he recommended me) whoſe Houſe is but a quarter of a League from the Fountain. This Lady, though ſomething in years, had a good Preſence, and ſuch remainders of Beauty ſtill as ſhew'd ſhe had been handſom in her Youth. She was well dreſs'd, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being taudry, and neat with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out affectation. I had ſent <hi>Bernard</hi> before to deliver her the Letter from her Friend, and ſhe received it very kindly; I was ſo lucky as to pleaſe her at firſt ſight, and ſhe uſed me with a great deal of reſpect. The good Hermit in his Letter acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her with my Quality, and my Diſguiſe, and injoyned her Secrecy
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:108168:49"/>in both, which ſhe promis'd me, and I found her as good as her Word. When I came to her firſt, ſhe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented her Daughter to me, whom I ſaluted like a Cavalier, but with that diſorder as you may imagine ſuch an unuſual Compliment put me into. She was exceeding handſom, and I found afterwards her Mind was as charming as her Face. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the firſt Ceremonies were over, I could not but take notice of the deep ſorrow that hung both upon the Mother and Daughter, occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion'd by the loſs of her Brother, who was kill'd at the Siege of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die,</hi> the remembrance of which of ten renewed their Tears, for they both deſcrib'd him to be a Man of extraordinary merit.</p>
               <p>The habitual Melancholy I had contracted, having leſſen'd my na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Chearfulneſs, I became a very ſuitable Companion for Madam <hi>de Mezelon,</hi> and her Daughter; and we enter'd into a ſtrict Friendſhip, but
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:108168:49"/>upon different grounds: for the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther knew who I was, but her Daughter did not, and ſo, in ſpight of all ſhe could do to reſiſt it, could not help falling into a violent Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for me. My Fate thus, rather than my Deſert, brought Love to meet me in whatever Shape I was. After I had been ſome days at <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zelon,</hi> I ſent <hi>Bernard</hi> away to <hi>Turin</hi> to enquire after the Marquis <hi>de St.</hi>—and to ſee of there were any likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of my being there conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently during my Exile. I wrote alſo to <hi>Paris,</hi> and Madam <hi>de Meze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> gave me a Direction to <hi>Sorgues,</hi> by which I might have Anſwers to my Letters. Poor <hi>Bernard</hi> could not leave me without a great deal of ſorrow, and could not forbear coming back again twenty times, to give me the beſt Advice he could for my Health, my Safety, and my Behaviour. When he was gone, I went to ſee <hi>Vaucluſe,</hi> and that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful Abode made me conſider
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:108168:50"/>all the Places which <hi>Petrarch</hi> and <hi>Laura</hi> had choſen there to ſpend the ſweeteſt Moments of their Love, and Life too, in ſo bleſſed a Retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. I ſaid to my ſelf, I had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been truly happy; for my De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to pleaſe others, had hitherto depriv'd me of the inchanting Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures which proceed from the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of two Hearts ſincerely affected to one another.</p>
               <p>Lovely <hi>Feliza</hi> (ſo was Madam <hi>de Mezelon</hi>'s Daughter nam'd) had a Woman to wait on her call'd <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſa,</hi> who had Wit enough; both theſe young Women did all that lay in their power to divert me; we went every day towards <hi>Vau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſe,</hi> becauſe that ſweet Place fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd us with Diſcourſe of what had formerly hapned there. I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood <hi>Italian,</hi> but <hi>Feliza</hi> and <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſa</hi> had not enough to read <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarch</hi>'s Poems; therefore I explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them, with abundance of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, all the tender, moving things
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:108168:50"/>in them. <hi>Feliza,</hi> who was as much delighted to hear me, ſtill look'd ſo languiſhingly upon me, that I, who was not to learn that ſilent Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, quickly apprehended the meaning of her Eyes; but I ſeem'd however not to underſtand her, and wiſh'd a thouſand times ſhe might never diſcover her Thoughts more plainly to me. But all to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; for poor <hi>Feliza</hi> could not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear making a Declaration of Love to me. I entertain'd it with as much confuſion as ſhe made it; and as Lovers are ingenious in tormenting themſelves, ſhe fancied my Heart was prepoſſeſs'd with ſome other Object; and her Jealouſie and Love together brought ſuch a Melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon her, that it injur'd her Beauty, and made me really pity her. Her Mother perceiv'd what was the Cauſe of her Melancholy, as well as I; for ſhe had been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the Myſteries of Love: but apprehending no Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:108168:51"/>in her Daughters Kindneſs to me, ſhe would not undeceive her, by diſcovering my Diſguiſe. For my part, I could not find in my heart to abuſe her any longer; but deſiring Madam <hi>de Mezelon</hi> to amuſe <hi>Thereſa,</hi> while I ſpoke with her Daughter, I went one day into her Chamber. I found her alone, lean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Head upon her Left-hand, her Eyes fix'd upon the Ground, in a Poſture exactly proper to expreſs Melancholy. The Habit under which I cover'd my Sex made her ſcrupulous of being ſo near me alone as I deſir'd, and therefore ſhe roſe up to call <hi>Thereſa;</hi> but I laid hold of her Gown, and ſtaid her. <hi>My dear</hi> Feliza, ſaid I to her, <hi>I conjure you by all the marks of Friendſhip you have hitherto ſhewn me, to let me ſpeak with you a little in private. Alas!</hi> anſwer'd <hi>Feliza, What can you ſay to me, which my ill Fortune does not already too well inform me of? I would undeceive you,</hi> replied I, <hi>of
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:108168:51"/>the Opinion you have, that I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible of the Affection you have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd to me; and withal give you the greateſt Proof of mine you can ever receive.</hi> At theſe Words ſhe look'd up, to diſcover in my Eyes, if ſhe could, what I had to ſay to her; and by the languiſhing of hers, I could eaſily perceive her Heart was really touch'd: At laſt I own'd to her, I could make her no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn for her Love but my Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and diſcover'd to her I was a Woman. But, <hi>Madam,</hi> in ſtead of quieting her Mind, at preſent this did but diſturb her more. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion ſhe was in for having open'd her Thoughts to me, made her bluſh; and her Circumſtances were very ſtrange, that ſhe ſhould be torment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a Paſſion, which ſhe could not ſtifle, though ſhe had never yet been fed with any Hopes, and now knew it was impoſſible for me to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie her.</p>
               <p>I did all I could to convince her,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:108168:52"/>that no Pleaſure is ſo refin'd and laſting as mutual Friend ſhip; which ſhe had much ado to believe: but at laſt in a few days her Reaſon wrought more with her, than all the Advice I could give her then: She overcame her Inclination, which I found next time I ſaw her had coſt her ſome Tears. From thence for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſhe grew reconciled to my Sex, and we ſpent above fifteen days together in a great deal of Tranquillity and Happineſs. We walk'd one Evening to the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain at <hi>Vaucluſe,</hi> where after a long Diſcourſe upon different Subjects, at laſt I fell aſleep with my Head up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Feliza</hi>'s Knees: At the ſame time two Horſemen paſs'd by us; <hi>Feliza</hi> did not know who they were, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they turn'd their Faces ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, and were not near enough to view them diſtinctly; yet one one of them brought the Image of that dear Brother, whom ſhe loved ſo tenderly, into her Mind. She
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:108168:52"/>wak'd me to ſhew him me; and though I ſaw him a good way off, I thought him an handſom Man.</p>
               <p>When we came home again, we went into Madam <hi>de Mezelon</hi>'s Chamber, who was quite over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelm'd with Grief. <hi>Ah, Cheva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier,</hi> ſaid ſhe to me, (for ſo I deſir'd her to call me) <hi>am I not very miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable? My Afflictions began to wear away with time, and I found my ſelf under a neceſſity of ſubmitting pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently to the loſs of my Son, when word was brought me, that he was ſeen paſs by an hundred Paces off the Houſe, juſt in the ſame Garb as when he took his leave of me.</hi> The tender Mother could not forbear weeping afreſh at a Remembrance ſo dear, and yet ſo afflicting; then we told her what we had ſeen, which ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded exceedingly to her Sorrow. I had much ado to pacifie her, telling her there were many People ſo like one another, that it was eaſie to be deceiv'd. I kept with her till mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:108168:53"/>and was retiring to my Chamber, when the Porter brought me a Note that was deliver'd him for me, in which I found theſe Words.</p>
               <p>I <hi>Am reſolv'd not to come into an Houſe which you have diſhonour'd, till I have made your Life pay for your Ingratitude. My own Eyes have been Witneſſes of that Diſgrace which Honour obliges me to waſh off in your Blood; and I have beſides too good Proofs of your Villany, ever to believe the contrary. I will expect you to morrow at Sun-riſing, at the ſame Place where I ſaw you yeſterday with my unworthy Siſter. Fail not to be there, to ſatisfie my juſt Revenge, unleſs you would have me do ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that may be worſe for you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Judge, <hi>Madam,</hi> how ſurpris'd I was to have a thing of this nature upon my Hands. I eaſily gueſs'd the Cauſe of it, and immediately
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:108168:53"/>went and ſhew'd the Challenge to Madam <hi>de Mezelon,</hi> who was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd at it. She waited impatient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for Day-light, to go to the Place appointed, whither ſhe went alone, and though ſhe was his Mother, was ſain to bear with her Son's Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, for it was really He. She ſmil'd at what he ſaid, and you may believe was not angry to ſee him ſo ſenſible of Honour. After ſhe had let him go on a little while in his Miſtake, ſhe undeceiv'd him, by tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him part of my Story, and the Secret of my Sex, which was now between the Mother, the Daughter, and the Son. He aggravated the trouble it was to him, to ſee his Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſuffer a Man to ſleep in her Lap; and added, he was juſt about to come and kill us both upon the Place, but that thinking his Siſter might be married in his abſence, he reſolv'd to inform himſelf well, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he committed ſo violent an Action; that he applied himſelf to
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:108168:54"/>a Man who had lived heretofore in the Houſe, who confeſs'd to him he ſaw me every day with <hi>Feliza</hi> about <hi>Vaucluſe,</hi> and that all the Neighbourhood was ſcandalis'd at it.</p>
               <p>Madam <hi>de Mezelon</hi> ſaid a great many things to him to my advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and when ſhe brought him in, preſented me to him. What made the beſt ſport, was, it was already current among all the Servants, that <hi>Mezelon</hi> had challeng'd me to fight with him; ſo that when he came to embrace me, the ſame People who believ'd we were Enemies, fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied I was married to his Siſter, and that the Buſineſs was to be kept private.</p>
               <p>After this firſt Interview, <hi>Meze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> took ſome time to refreſh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and to put himſelf in a Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to appear decently before me. Well, <hi>Madam,</hi> what ſhall I ſay? The Brother too, as ſoon as he came home, thought as advantageouſly of
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:108168:54"/>me as his Siſter did when I came thither firſt for Refuge. I was in <hi>Feliza</hi>'s Chamber when he came to viſit me, and that pretty Creature, either preſagingly, or in raillery, told me, ſhe was ſure her Brother would not ſee me long without paying Homage to my Charms. As ſoon as he ſate down, <hi>Well, dear Brother,</hi> ſaid ſhe to him, <hi>would you not think me as guilty now, as you did yeſterday, if you did not know the Truth? Remember, Siſter,</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd <hi>Mezelon, I was not angry with you; for I think I forgave you in my Heart: But I queſtion whether I ſhall not have more cauſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of this Cavalier, than before, and carry my Reſentment ſo far, as to challenge him to give me another Meeting at</hi> Petrarch<hi>'s Well. I am ſuch a Coward ſtill,</hi> ſaid I, <hi>ever ſince laſt Night, that you may wait there for me again to no purpoſe, as you did this Morning. Truly, Madam,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied <hi>Mezelon, I believe if you had
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:108168:55"/>been in my place, you would have done what I did. Seeing an hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom Man in a very familiar poſture with my Siſter, I inquir'd if they were married; and being told they were not, after that, I think — I find no fault with what you did,</hi> ſaid I, interrupting him; <hi>I only wiſh it may teach you never to judge by bare Appearances, let them be never ſo ſtrong.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this Viſit, which laſted a good while, I found <hi>Mezelon</hi> had a great deal of Wit; and thoſe he made me afterwards, convinc'd me that he really loved me. How was it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, <hi>Madam,</hi> to breathe the Air of <hi>Vaucluſe</hi> five or ſix Months, and not be ſenſible of Love? By what paſs'd then in my Heart I plainly perceiv'd I had never yet been in Love, but had only ſuffer'd my ſelf to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lov'd. I had not till now felt thoſe pleaſing pains which ſeize upon one's Heart before it is firmly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin'd to abandon it felf wholly
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:108168:55"/>to Love; I had always been igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the lively pleaſures it injoys in the beginnings of a Paſſion; thoſe trifles which have ſuch great effects; in a Word, thoſe little things which indifferent People call folly, but which make the moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful employment of Lovers. I forgot all my misfortunes, the only one I fear'd was being forc'd to part with <hi>Mezelon.</hi> I would not ſo much as ſuppoſe that <hi>Bernard</hi>'s return could ingage me to a Journey from thence; and I accommodated my Morals to my Love and often flatter'd my ſelf, that the hatred my Husband ſhew'd to me, was a ſufficient Diſpenſation from my Conjugal Faith. In ſhort, <hi>Madam,</hi> I forbore nothing but what came too cloſe both upon my own Honour as well as his, and made no manner of ſcruple of all the reſt.</p>
               <p>Moſt Women in the World, if they were ſincere, would freely own
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:108168:56"/>what I confeſs now; for I do not believe I am the firſt Example in this kind. <hi>Mezelon</hi>'s Return brought a great many People of Quality to ſee him, for he was generally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, and all who came were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted to hear the Deſcription of his ſuppoſed Death and Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which we had not yet got from him. Being one Evening with his Mother, and Siſter, and one of his Kinſwomen, we put him upon the Relation of his Adventures in <hi>Candie,</hi> which he comply'd with in theſe Terms.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="history">
               <head>The Hiſtory of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zelon.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Went on Roard the Duke of <hi>Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort</hi>'s Ship, and I cannot tell you, Ladies, whether our Voyage was ſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my or calm; all I can ſay, is, That I was ſick all the while I was at Sea,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:108168:56"/>never was upon the Deck till we ſaw <hi>Candie;</hi> and the Inconvenience I ſuffer'd during the whole Paſſage, hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred me from learning any of the Sea-terms. As ſoon as I landed, I quickly recovered my Health again, and made it my Buſineſs to be as near the General as I could, whoſe Example was ſufficient to inſpire us all with generous Emulation. You muſt needs be inform'd of what paſs'd at the Siege by the Publick News, ſo that I ſhall not enter into the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, which cannot but be tedious to thoſe that know them already: I ſuppoſe it is my Story, and not that of the <hi>Turks,</hi> or the <hi>Venetians,</hi> you deſire to learn; therefore I ſhall tell you, That in the loſt Battel I was dangerouſly wounded I was, I ſaid before, near the Duke of <hi>Beaufort</hi>'s Perſon, who had ſent his <hi>Aydes de Camp</hi> to carry his Orders into ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral parts of the Field; he command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me alſo to bring on ſome Troops to
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:108168:57"/>ſuſtain a Battalion which began to give ground to the Enemy. When I had executed his Orders, I return'd, but could not find him any where, and immediately it was reported a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us that he was kill'd. I thruſt my ſelf in among the thickeſt, to learn the truth, and got nothing for my pains but two deep Wounds upon my Head and my Shoulder, which how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever kept me not from being one of the laſt that made good their Retreat into the Town. The ill ſucceſs of this Day made them refuſe to let me into my Quarters; being much wounded, and not yet dreſs'd, I was in great diſtreſs, not knowing where to go, and was beginning to faint, when the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch of <hi>Candie,</hi> and his eldeſt Daughter, lighting upon me in that Condition, charitably took me into their Houſe. Their Aſſiſtance came very ſeaſonably; but what was then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to me, was like afterwards <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> me.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:108168:57"/>
The Patriarch's Daughter, whoſe Name was <hi>Euſtochia,</hi> dreſs'd my Wounds, and I had reaſon to thank her for her Care; but I have always held this Maxim, <hi>That Beneſits re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd from a Fair Hand, are more obliging than thoſe we receive from a Deformed Object. Euſtochia</hi> was one of the laſt; for ſhe had the uglieſt Face I ever ſaw, which ſhe conceal'd from me as much as ſhe could; and my Covntry-men em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barqu'd, and ſail'd away, without my knowing of it. I was reckon'd among the Slain, becauſe I had not appear'd in the Town ſince the Battel; and my Hoſt durſt not own he had reſus'd to take me in: ſo that our Forces went away, and I was left behind.</p>
               <p>When I was cured, <hi>Euſtochia</hi> look'd upon my Heart as a due Recompence for the good Offices ſhe had dene me; but though I ow'd her a great deal, I could not extend my Gratitude ſo ſar. She had a Siſter, indeed, to
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:108168:58"/>whom I would willingly have been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden for my Life, and without that Tie, would have been glad to have diſcharg'd to her the Obligations I had to <hi>Euſtochia;</hi> who perceiving I look'd kindly on her, and gueſſing what Thoughts ſhe had inſpir'd me with, immediately chang'd her Love into Hatred, and a deſire of deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me. As nothing can be more Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous than the Heart of a <hi>Greek,</hi> ſo nothing is more Violent than their Reſentment. The Town ſurrendred, as you have heard; and the <hi>Turks</hi> made their Victorious Entry into it. <hi>Euſtochia</hi> got acquainted with a <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizary</hi> who deplor'd the loſs of his Brother, that was kill'd in the laſt Fight; ſhe inform'd her ſelf what kind of Man he was, what Station he had in the Army, and then told him a few days after, ſhe believ'd I had kill'd him. The <hi>Janizary,</hi> without conſidering there was no likelihood of her knowing what ſhe told him,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:108168:58"/>thought of nothing but revenging his Brother's Death, and expreſs'd great earneſtneſs to have me in his power; which ſhe engag'd to bring about, But her charitable Siſter diſcovering her Deſign, would not ſuffer me to periſh ſo unjuſtly; and there being no time to be loſt, took a Reſolution as bold, as it was generous.</p>
               <p>She knew her Father was too weak a Man to oppoſe <hi>Euſtochia</hi>'s Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſo it would be Labour loſt to meddle with him: But underſtanding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> let the Treaty of Capitulation be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fring'd, eſpecially in any thing that concern'd our Nation, ſhe order'd her Buſineſs ſo as to be brought before him, and ſpoke to him thus in <hi>Greek,</hi> which he underſtood very well. <hi>I come, Sir,</hi> ſaid ſhe to him, <hi>to deſire Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, not againſt any of your Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, or the Officers of your Army, but againſt my own Siſter, whoſe wicked Mind has preval'd with her
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:108168:59"/>to commit ſo black an Action, as I cannot think of it without horrour. A young</hi> Frenchman <hi>lay at my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Houſe: It is true, my Siſter, ſeeing his Life in a great deal of danger, took a great deal of care of him, and has cured him of two deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Hurts; but now, to her ſhame, and his almoſt unavoidable deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, ſhe has chang'd her mind, and would take away that Life ſhe has preſerv'd. And ſo to add Impoſture to her Eury ſhe has made the</hi> Jani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zary Ach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aec <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Frenchman <hi>kill'd his Brother in the laſt Sally, and has promis'd to put this innocent Victim into his Hands, which ſhe ſacrifices more to her own Revenge, than to</hi> Achi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dec<hi>'s Grief. Begin now, Sir, to eſtabliſh an Opinion of your Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and take ſome ſpeedy courſe, that my Siſter may not have leiſure to execute her cruel Reſolution.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Auguſta (ſo was my Preſerver
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:108168:59"/>nam'd)</hi> pronounc'd theſe Words with ſo much Grace and Courage, that they moved the <hi>Grand Vizir,</hi> who immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately ſent me an Officer, and twenty Soldiers; and they came very ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably to me, for an hour later <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſta</hi>'s Pity would have done me no good. I was brought before the <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zir,</hi> who was pleas'd not to diſlike me: He had <hi>French</hi> enough to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand me; but he ſpeaks it not himſelf. Though I do not ſing very well, <hi>Euſtochia</hi> and <hi>Auguſta</hi> were ſometimes delighted with my Voice. The laſt of them knowing the <hi>Grand Vizir</hi> lov'd Muſick, let him know, that if he would command me to ſing, I was capable of diverting him: So that after he had ask'd me ſeveral Queſtions concerning the Perſon and the Conqueſts of our Great Monarch, he fell inſenſibly upon the Addreſs of the <hi>French,</hi> and the Perfection to which they have improv'd all Arts; particularly, Poetry, and Muſick.
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:108168:60"/>From this, he apply'd himſelf to me, and with ſurpriſing Civility told me, he was inform'd I could ſing, and believ'd I would not deny him the ſatisfaction of letting him hear me. I had learnt ſome of the famous <hi>Lambert</hi>'s Tunes, which I ſang to him the beſt I could, and had cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly offended more curious Ears; but the Vizir was very well ſatisfied with me. He ſent for <hi>Achidec,</hi> and commanded him to do me no Injury; nay, farther, took the pains to tell him, That what <hi>Euſtochia</hi> had ſaid to him, was onely to make him the Inſtrument of her Revenge; it being impoſſible for her to know, with any certainty, that I had kill'd his Brother.</p>
               <p>After that, the <hi>Vizir</hi> diſmiſs'd me, giving me a very fine Scimitar at parting. Perhaps you may have heard, that one of the Articles of the Capitulation ran, <hi>That thoſe</hi> Candiots <hi>who had no mind to live
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:108168:60"/>under the Government of the</hi> Turks, <hi>ſhould have a Months time to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw whither they pleas'd.</hi> Some of them went into <hi>Sicily,</hi> and others into <hi>Italy:</hi> for my part, I deſign'd to embarque with thoſe who ſaild in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Sicily,</hi> where the <hi>Meſſineſes</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to take Arms; but when I men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd it to my pretty <hi>Auguſta,</hi> her Tears and Sighs overcame all my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions. I promis'd her not to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake her, and aſſur'd her ſhould always diſpoſe how ſhe thought fit of a Life ſhe had ſo generouſly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd.</p>
               <p>The inraged <hi>Euſtochia</hi> ſet her Wits at work again to deſtroy me, and had like to have ſucceeded, as you ſhall hear. You may be ſure, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I got out of the Patriarch's Houſe, I went thither no more. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſta</hi> deſir'd a Kinſman of hers to provide me a Lodging, where I might be while I ſtaid there. <hi>Euſtochia</hi> having notice of it, cunningly ſuborn'd
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:108168:61"/>a <hi>Turk</hi> to ruine me; ſhe told him, he muſt get acquainted with me, and then put me upon Diſcourſe of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. This <hi>Turk</hi> underſtood <hi>Italian,</hi> which ſhe knew I ſpoke; and that made her pitch upon him. It is ſuch an unpardonable Crime for a <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> to talk to a <hi>Turk</hi> about matters of Religion, that now ſhe thought ſhe had laid an unavoidable Snare for me.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Turk</hi> thus inſtructed, made it his Buſineſs to be acquainted with me; to inſinuate himſelf into me, and make me the leſs ſhy of talking with him, he now and then did me ſome ſmall Kindneſs or other. At laſt, after ſeveral Diſcourſes upon indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Subjects, he drew me on by degrees to diſpute with him about the Myſteries of our Faith; which I did, without the leaſt thought of convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing him of thoſe Truths, becauſe I had always obſerv'd him to be an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate Believer of the <hi>Alcoran.</hi>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:108168:61"/>However, he ſo well remembred what I had ſaid of our Religion, that he did not loſe one word; and then, as he and <hi>Euſtochia</hi> had agreed, went to the <hi>Grand Vizir,</hi> and inform'd him that I endeavour'd to convert him. Never the leaſt dreaming of this Deſign againſt me, as I was coming one day from <hi>Auguſta,</hi> I was ſeis'd by twelve <hi>Turks,</hi> who by force dragg'd me into a dark Priſon, abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing me all the way, as I gueſs'd by their uſage of me; for I underſtood not their Language. <hi>Auguſta</hi> hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of my Misfortune, preſumed once more to go to the <hi>Grand Vizir,</hi> whom ſhe endeavoured to perſuade, that all this was but a continuation of her Siſters implacable Fury againſt me. She repreſented me very incapable of the Crime I was accuſed of, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought him to ſuſpend his Judgment, till ſhe could find out ſome means to clear the Truth. My Perſon and Voice had not been ſo diſagreeable to
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:108168:62"/>him, but that, as good luck would have it for me, he remembred both, and allow'd her twelve Days to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie me in. But fearing her Siſter would make uſe of the Patriarch's Authority to hinder her Endeavours, ſhe retired to a Relation's Houſe of hers, that ſhe might be at liberty to go abroad when ſhe pleas'd.</p>
               <p>Several Days paſs'd without her being able to learn any thing that could help her to ſerve me; and the Term which the <hi>Grand Vizir</hi> ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ready to expire, all the Town expected to ſee me Impall'd; when a young Wench, that liv'd in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch's Houſe, came to ſee <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta</hi> in her Retreat, and told her, that <hi>Euſtochia</hi> often convers'd with the <hi>Turk</hi> whom ſhe had corrupted. <hi>Auguſta</hi> preſently engag'd the Maid to declare what ſhe knew before the <hi>Vizir,</hi> and then went to deſire him to confront me with my Accuſer. This Miniſter immediately caus'd me to
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:108168:62"/>be brought before him, and ſending for <hi>Euſtochia</hi> and the <hi>Turk,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him by <hi>Alla</hi> to ſpeak the Truth, and what had moved him to accuſe me in that manner. My Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and the Oath he was oblig'd to take, ſo ſtagger'd him, that he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd <hi>Euſtochia</hi> had hir'd him to ſay what he did againſt me; that indeed I had talk'd with him of the Chriſtian Religion, but that he began the Diſcourſe; and that far from uſing any Arguments to convert him, I had onely anſwered the Queſtions he put to me. The <hi>Grand Vizir</hi> thus ſatisfied of my Innocence, condemn'd the <hi>Turk</hi> to the ſame Puniſhment which was intended for me, He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd <hi>Euſtochia</hi> ſeverely, commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Auguſta</hi>'s Generoſity, and ſet me at Liberty. And knowing the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch was angry with <hi>Auguſta</hi> for leaving him without his Conſent, he oblig'd him to forgivt her. I preſs'd him earneſtly to pardon the <hi>Turk,</hi>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:108168:63"/>but to no purpofe; all I could get from him was, <hi>That ſuch Oſſences as thoſe were not to be forgiven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From this time forwards <hi>Auguſta</hi> was urgent with me to forſake a place where ſoon or late I ſhould certainly come to ſome miſchief. I follow'd her advice, extreamly griev'd to leave her expos'd to her Siſters ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred. I expreſs'd all the gratitude to her at parting, which ſhe might juſtly claim from an Heart fo truly ſenſible of all the extraordinary fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours ſhe had done me. I ſet Sail with ſome <hi>Candiots,</hi> who choſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire into <hi>Sicily,</hi> and arriv'd there without any accident. I ſtaid there but a week, taking the opportunity of returning into <hi>France</hi> upon a Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant-Man that brought Silks from <hi>Meſſina.</hi> You may imagine my Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page was not very ſplended, all I had in the World was the Scimiter the Grand Vizir gave me: But when I came to <hi>Toulon,</hi> I made what haſte I
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:108168:63"/>could to get to <hi>Marſellis,</hi> where I met with a Merchant who furniſhed me with Money, and Clothes, and and Horſes for my ſelf, and my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant. After ſome ſmall ſtay there, I came directly hither, where conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the report that was ſpread of my Death, I queſtion not but my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn is very ſurprizing.</p>
               <p>Mezelon <hi>having concluded his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, we ſpent ſome time in ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him abundance of Queſtions, all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> anſwered with a great deal of Wit, which furniſh'd us with Diſcourſe enough, eſpecially about</hi> Auguſta, <hi>on which Subject I pinch'd him pretty cloſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>At laſt,</hi> Madam, Bernard <hi>came back to me; he had been at</hi> Yurin, <hi>and not finding the Marquis</hi> de St.— <hi>there, went from thence to</hi> Paris, <hi>though I gave him no order to do ſo; but the kindneſs he had for me, made him preſume up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:108168:64"/>on Priviledges which few of his rank are allow'd. He told me my Husband was gone from</hi> Paris, <hi>but no body knew which way; that the Preſident was dead, and his Lady retir'd into a Convent, that the Prince lived Peaceably with his Wife; the Marquiſs</hi> de St.— <hi>was deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately ſick, and that the Duke had heard him relate what had happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to me without betraying the leaſt concern. I was as indifferent as he, and minded what</hi> Bernard <hi>told me but little; for I learnt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> what had paſs'd in my buſineſs, nor was a jot the wiſer how to behave my ſelf for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. But the arrival of the good Hermit interrupted my ſatisfaction a little; he excus'd his not having writ, or ſent to me, by reaſon of a Journey he was oblig'd to make as far as the</hi> Charterhouſe <hi>of</hi> Grenoble. <hi>and told me at his return he had learnt that</hi> Spichetti <hi>was like to
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:108168:64"/>have died with grief, when he found I was eſcap'd from him; and when he was well of his Fever, writ word to my Husband, that if he would come to</hi> Avignon, <hi>he would put me into his Hands; that my Husband came thither Poſt, and both of them us'd their induſtry to diſcover where I was; that the Gardner being ſuſpected to have aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted my flight, had been very ill handled, and had told them all he knew. And I believe, added the Hermit, if they continue to ſearch for you, it will be no hard matter for them to find you here. I deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him at firſt to tell me what he had to ſay before Madam</hi> de Meze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, <hi>and her Son and Daughter, who with all the Civility in the World, aſſur'd me, I ſhould ſuffer no vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence while I was there.</hi> Bernard <hi>diſlik'd my truſting ſo many Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with my Buſineſs, and his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholly upon that account made me
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:108168:65"/>bear with a great many of his ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Arguments. He perceiv'd too, there was a good underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing between</hi> Mezelon <hi>and me, which nothing but abſence could hinder from proceeding further. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he advis'd me to go from thence; but I wanted ſtronger Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to perſwade me to that, than his Counſel: not but that I appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended I ſhould be very miſerable if my Husband once found me out; but I could not find in my Heart to leave a place where I lov'd, and was ſure I was belov'd.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>One day, as the Hermit and I were diſcourſing what was the beſt courſe for me to take, word was brought that ſome Strangers on Horſeback deſired to ſpeak with Madam</hi> de Mezelon, <hi>and her Son.</hi> Feliza<hi>'s Chamber, where I was, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over againſt the Draw-bridge, whom ſhould I ſee at the Gate but my Husband, and the</hi> Italian <hi>who conducted him thither?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:108168:65"/>
                  <hi>I need not tell you,</hi> Madam, <hi>what Menaces to terrifie, and what Arguments he uſed to perſwade Madam</hi> de Mezelon <hi>to deliver me to him. She reſiſted all he could ſay with equal conſtancy, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved not to let me go, till his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon had got the better of his Anger. My Husband had ſo little to object to her way of proceeding, that at laſt he begg'd of her to be the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatrix between us, ſubmitting all our differences to her, which ſhe would by no means hear of till I gave my conſent. You may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,</hi> Madam, <hi>my concerns were in too good hands to decline this of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer; ſo that our reconciliation might not appear forc'd, my Husband was to withdraw for ſome days, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which he and I were to have a meeting, at which Madam</hi> de Meze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon <hi>ſhould be preſent. Monſieur</hi> de Mezelon <hi>too gave his word, that I ſhould not leave his Houſe till our
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:108168:66"/>Agreement was perfectly conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, or came to nothing. The good Hermit, who was ſtill at</hi> Mezelon, <hi>would not ſtir till he ſaw the iſſue of my Buſineſs, and was very ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable in appeaſing my Husbands Mind, and diſpoſing him to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concil'd to me. But whether it were by Inſtinct, or particular Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, which he had ground for, when he took leave of him, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd him not to be ſo open to every body, and to have a care whom he truſted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The</hi> Italian <hi>was vex'd to the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Heart, to ſee how fair a way we were in towards an accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and therefore to keep it back as much as he could, he perſwaded my Husband to go from</hi> Mezelon; <hi>but yet all the Reaſons he could urge were inſufficient to hinder him from returning at the day ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed. I will aſſure you, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, that how favourably ſoever I
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:108168:66"/>thought of</hi> Mezelon, <hi>I could not but be ſenſibly touch'd at my Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band's mildneſs, and condeſcention. He found me in my own Clothes, ſo modeſtly dreſs'd, that he had no cauſe to find any fault. The Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony Madam</hi> de Mezelon <hi>gave him of my good behaviour, calm'd his Mind extreamly, and I had more reaſon to pitty him, than to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend his diſpleaſure. I endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to juſtifie my ſelf in every thing had been told him, not omitting any Circumſtance that I had been accuſed of; but what moſt ſurpriz'd him, was, my asking him to clear me of the imputation of deſigning to murther him. I freely confeſs'd I had too eaſily entertain'd the Prince's, the Preſident's, and the Duke's Addreſſes; but when I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted him how Madam</hi> la Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidente <hi>drew me into theſe kind of intrigues, and ſhew'd him how things really were, he was ſorry he
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:108168:67"/>had left me expos'd to the Husbands Love, and the Wives counterfeit Virtue. He imputed all the errours of my Youth to the exceeding ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity of the Rules he had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd, and his own wilfulneſs in forcing me to be ſo great with Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> la Preſidente. <hi>I forgot to tell you, that</hi> Spichetti <hi>dreaded my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering to my Husband how he had perſecuted me, and the Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor had more weighty Reaſons to keep him from coming along with him to</hi> Mezelon: <hi>And indeed when I did inform him how much the</hi> I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talian <hi>had injur'd me, all which I proved by the Hermit who had heard of it by other Hands, and by my own Servants who had been witneſſes of his Villany, he appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be mightily troubled, and I needed to ſay little more to prevail with him to forgive all my extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gances; ſo that this interview, which was to have been only the forerun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:108168:67"/>of our Reconciliation, almoſt quite concluded it. I was really ſorry for all my indiſcreet Actions, and was diſpoſing my ſelf to ſpend the Remainder of my Life in ſuch a manner as might efface all the ill Impreſſions he had entertain'd of me; when of a ſudden he fell into a Swoon, which at firſt we attributed to the moving tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our Meeting; but we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd our Opinion, when coming to himſelf again, he complain'd of intolerable Pains, and then relaps'd ſo often into fainting Fits, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter enduring two days continual Torment, they at laſt kill'd him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He made a Will, in which he juſtified me of all he had laid to my Charge, and gave me all that the Law could allow me, on con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition I ſhould marry Monſieur</hi> de Mezelon. <hi>Having heard how faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully</hi> Bernard <hi>and my Woman had ſerved me, he forgot not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:108168:68"/>
                  <hi>The more we examined his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper, the more reaſon we had to believe he was poyſon'd; and he ſaid ſomething of it to him who was with him when he died. We had him open'd, and found evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Tokens of the Poyſon</hi> Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chetti <hi>had given him. I ſent to</hi> Avignon <hi>to apprehend him, but Heaven had already taken care to puniſh him. He whom I ſent, brought us word, that one of his own Servants had murder'd him, and was gone away with all his Money and Jewels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My Husband's Death really af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted me; but Time, and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation every body endeavour'd to give me by degrees wip'd off my Tears. However, I would not marry again till his Will was perform'd; and though</hi> Mezelon <hi>preſs'd me ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry cloſely, I would not conſent till I had been a Widow an whole year; and then, to the great joy of his
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:108168:68"/>Mother and Siſter, I no longer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd the Accompliſhment of his Deſires. Ever ſince, my onely Care has been to pleaſe my Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and by that means render my Life eaſie and innocent. After ſome Buſineſs I have here is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatch'd, I intend to go back to him again, and hope I ſhall never have occaſion to be from him any more.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Counteſs of</hi> Marignan <hi>was extremely ſatisfied with the Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Madam</hi> de Mezelon <hi>had enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd her with, admiring the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Accidents of her Life. But it growing late, ſhe took leave of her, promiſing to meet her next day at the ſame Place, and recompenſe her with an Account of her own Story.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>The End of the Firſt Part.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:108168:69"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of ſome <hi>Novels</hi> and <hi>Plays</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Bent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> and <hi>S. Magnes.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <label>NOVELS.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 <hi>ZElinda,</hi> a ſam'd <hi>Romance.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Happy Slave,</hi> in three Parts.</item>
                     <item>3 Count <hi>Brion.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4 Count <hi>Gabales.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>5 <hi>Hatige,</hi> or the Amours of the King of <hi>Tamaran.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>6 Mad. <hi>Lavalier</hi> and the King of <hi>France.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>7 Madam and the Duke of <hi>Guiſe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>8 Mad. <hi>Colonna</hi>'s Memoirs.</item>
                     <item>9 Queen of <hi>Majork,</hi> two Parts.</item>
                     <item>10 Don <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> King of <hi>Portugal.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>11 Heroine Muſquetier.</item>
                     <item>12 Princeſs of <hi>Cleves.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>13 Obliging Miſtreſs.</item>
                     <item>14 Fatal Prudence.</item>
                     <item>15 Princeſs of <hi>Fez.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:108168:69"/>
16 Diſorders of Love.</item>
                     <item>17 Triumph of Love.</item>
                     <item>18 Victorious Lovers.</item>
                     <item>19 <hi>Almanzor</hi> and <hi>Almanzaida.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>20 Earl of <hi>Eſſex</hi> and Qu. <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>21 <hi>Neopolitan,</hi> or, the Defender of his Miſtreſs.</item>
                     <item>22 <hi>Nicoſtratis.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>23 Amorous Abbeſs.</item>
                     <item>24 <hi>Homais</hi> Queen of <hi>Tunis.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>25 Pilgrim, in two Parts.</item>
                     <item>26 <hi>Meroveus,</hi> Prince of the Blood-Royal of <hi>France.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>27 Life of the Duke of <hi>Guiſe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>28 Extravagant Poet.</item>
                     <item>29 <hi>Memoires Gallant.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>30 Inſtruction for a Young Noble-Man.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>PLAYS.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Tartuff,</hi> or the <hi>French</hi> Puritan.</item>
                     <item>2 Forc'd Mariage, or the Jealous Bridegroom.</item>
                     <item>3 <hi>Engliſh Monſieur.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4 All miſtaken, or the Mad Couple.</item>
                     <item>5 Generous Enemies, or the Ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Lovers.</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:108168:70"/>
6 The Plain-Dealer.</item>
                     <item>7 <hi>Sertorius,</hi> a Tragedy.</item>
                     <item>8 <hi>Nero,</hi> a Tragedy.</item>
                     <item>9 <hi>Sophonisba,</hi> or <hi>Hannibal</hi>'s Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw.</item>
                     <item>10 <hi>Gloriana,</hi> or the Court of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus Caeſar.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>11 <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great.</item>
                     <item>12 <hi>Mithridates</hi> King of <hi>Pontus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>13 <hi>Oedipus</hi> King of <hi>Thebes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>14 <hi>Caeſar Borgia.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>15 <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> or the Force of Love.</item>
                     <item>16 Madam <hi>Fickle,</hi> or the Witty Falſe One.</item>
                     <item>17 The Fond Husband, or the Plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Siſters.</item>
                     <item>18 Eſquire <hi>Old-Sap,</hi> or the Night-Adventures.</item>
                     <item>19 Fool turn'd Critick.</item>
                     <item>20 Virtuous Wife, or Good Luck at laſt.</item>
                     <item>21 The Fatal Wager.</item>
                     <item>22 <hi>Andromache.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>23 Country Wit.</item>
                     <item>24 <hi>Caliſto,</hi> or the Chaſte Nymph.</item>
                     <item>25 Deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in two Parts.</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:108168:70"/>
26 Ambitious Stateſman, or the Loyal Favourite.</item>
                     <item>27 Miſery of Civil War.</item>
                     <item>28 The Murder of the Duke of <hi>Gloceſter.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>29 <hi>Thyeſtes,</hi> a Tragedy.</item>
                     <item>30 <hi>Hamlet</hi> Prince of <hi>Denmark,</hi> a Tragedy.</item>
                     <item>31 The Orphan, or the Unhappy Marriage.</item>
                     <item>32 The Soldiers Fortune.</item>
                     <item>33 <hi>Tamerlain</hi> the Great.</item>
                     <item>34 Mr. <hi>Limber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>,</hi> or th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>d Keeper.</item>
                     <item>35 Miſtaken Huſband.</item>
                     <item>36 Notes of <hi>Morocco,</hi> by the Wits.</item>
                     <item>37 <hi>Eſſex</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> or the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Favourite.</item>
                     <item>38 Virtue Betray'd, or <hi>Anna Bullen.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>39 King <hi>Leare.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>40 <hi>Abdellazor,</hi> or the <hi>Moor</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge.</item>
                     <item>41 Town-Fop, or Sir <hi>Tim. Tawdery.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>42 <hi>Rare en tout,</hi> a <hi>French</hi> Comedy.</item>
                     <item>43 <hi>Moor</hi> of <hi>Venice.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>44 Country Wife.</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:108168:71"/>
45 City Politicks.</item>
                     <item>46 Duke of <hi>Guiſe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>47 Rehearſal.</item>
                     <item>48 King and no King.</item>
                     <item>49 <hi>Philaſter,</hi> or Love lies a Bleeding.</item>
                     <item>50 Maids Tragedy.</item>
                     <item>51 Grateful Servant.</item>
                     <item>52 Strange Diſcovery.</item>
                     <item>53 Atheiſt, or the Second Part of the Soldiers Fortune.</item>
                     <item>54 Wit without Money.</item>
                     <item>55 Little Thief.</item>
                     <item>56 Valiant <hi>Scot.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>57 <hi>Conſtantine.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>58 <hi>Valentinian.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>59 Amorous Prince.</item>
                     <item>60 <hi>Dutch</hi> Lovers.</item>
                     <item>61 Woman Rules.</item>
                     <item>62 Reformation.</item>
                     <item>63 <hi>Hero</hi> and <hi>Leander.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>64 Love-Tricks.</item>
                     <item>65 <hi>Julius Caeſar.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>66 Fatal Jealouſie.</item>
                     <item>67 Monſieur <hi>Ragou.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
